<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Capitalism on Class Letters</title>
    <link>https://classletters.org/tags/capitalism/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Capitalism on Class Letters</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2025 21:52:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://classletters.org/tags/capitalism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Theory of the Innovative Organization by William Lazonick</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/lazonick/theory_of_innovative_organization/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2025 21:52:32 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/lazonick/theory_of_innovative_organization/</guid>
      <description>An excerpt from William Lazonick&amp;rsquo;s terrific work &amp;ldquo;Business Organization and the Myth of the Market Economy&amp;rdquo;, a book that offers a critique of what a &amp;lsquo;market economy&amp;rsquo; is purported to be, through an evaluation of the strategies and economic histories of businesses within what can be called &amp;ldquo;actually existing capitalism&amp;rdquo;.&#xA;Here, at the risk of a small amount of repetition, I shall supplement that discussion by focusing on the nature of fixed costs, the different sources of uncertainty the innovative organization faces, and the relation between organizational capability and technological change.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decision-Making in a Good Society: The Case for Nested Councils by Stephen R. Shalom</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/decision_making/decision_making_postcap/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 06:18:49 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/decision_making/decision_making_postcap/</guid>
      <description>Stephen R. Shalom is emeritus professor of Political Science at William Paterson University of New Jersey, USA. He is a member of the editorial board of New Politics, and a long-time activist in peace and justice movements. Among other works, he is the author of Which Side Are You On? An Introduction to Politics (Longman, 2003), &amp;ldquo;Parpolity: A Political System for a Good Society,&amp;rdquo; in Real Utopia: Participatory Society for the 21st Century, ed.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cancer Prevention and Screening by Jason Fung; The Cancer Code</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/public_health/cancer_code/cancer_code_pt2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 23:41:44 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/public_health/cancer_code/cancer_code_pt2/</guid>
      <description>This is part 2 of the post on Jason Fung&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;Cancer Code&amp;rsquo;. I found this a remarkable case point in the iatrogenic potential of public health interventions in which the effect on mortality is masked by a surrogate of survival; early detection. When tracked for long enough time, early detection does more harm than good, and thus, fails as a successful surrogate. You can find part one here.&#xA;I encourage everyone to read the entirety of Jason&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;The Cancer Code&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A False Dawn by Jason Fung; The Cancer Code</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/public_health/cancer_code/cancer_code/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Feb 2024 23:41:44 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/public_health/cancer_code/cancer_code/</guid>
      <description>This post will be in two parts, both of which I find are illustrative of the difficulties of public health strategies. One makes particularly obvious the severe misanthropic consequences of profit seeking drives in the areas of health and medicine, and the second is a remarkable case point in the iatrogenic potential of public health interventions which may be completely benevolent in intention &amp;ndash; something that all states irrespective of political structure must address.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
