<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Culture-Critic on Class Letters</title><link>https://classletters.org/tags/culture-critic/</link><description>Recent content in Culture-Critic on Class Letters</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Mar 2023 10:59:16 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://classletters.org/tags/culture-critic/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Race into Culture: A Critical Genealogy of Cultural Identity by Walter Benn Michaels</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/walter-benn-michaels/geneology-race-into-culture/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Mar 2023 10:59:16 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/walter-benn-michaels/geneology-race-into-culture/</guid><description>Due to the prolific number of footnotes that Michael&amp;rsquo;s article contains, the essay will simply be linked to here. It is an important walk through the trajectories that various essentialist concepts have taken in the course of modern Northern American history. What surprised me most was this quasi-progess &amp;mdash; where it appears that the concept of race has been disposed of, it&amp;rsquo;s kernel is carried over into a different, yet sadly, familial form.</description></item><item><title>Soviet Literature by Maxim Gorky</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/maxim-gorky/soviet-literature/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 08:06:39 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/maxim-gorky/soviet-literature/</guid><description>Herein is a speech delivered in August 1934, and published in 1935. It reappeared in Gorky, Radek, Bukharin, Zhdanov and others “Soviet Writers’ Congress 1934,” page 25-69, Lawrence &amp;amp; Wishart, 1977, and was transcribed by Jose Braz for the Marxists Internet Archive.
The role of the labour processes, which have converted a two-Legged animal into man and created the basic elements of culture, has never been investigated as deeply and thoroughly as it deserves.</description></item></channel></rss>