<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mythology on Class Letters</title>
    <link>https://classletters.org/tags/mythology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Mythology on Class Letters</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2025 01:51:19 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://classletters.org/tags/mythology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The &#39;Lethal Chamber&#39; in Eugenic Thought: an excerpt from Breeding Superman: Nietzsche, Race and Eugenics in Edwardian and Interwar Britain by Dan Stone</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/nietzsche/breeding-superman-eugenics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2025 01:51:19 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/nietzsche/breeding-superman-eugenics/</guid>
      <description>Chapter five from Breeding Superman: Nietzsche, Race and Eugenics in Edwardian and Interwar Britain by Dan Stone.&#xA;As we have seen, before the First World War, and in some circles until well into the interwar period, eugenics &amp;mdash; literally, ‘well born’ or ‘good stocks’&amp;mdash; was the height of sophisticated, ‘progressive’ thought.1 Across Europe, the novels and plays of the period, such as H. G. Wells’s The New Machiavelli (1911) and George Bernard Shaw’s Man and Superman (1905), are suffused with the language of race-regeneration and fears of physical deterioration.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Marx, Race and Neoliberalism by Adolph Reed Jr.</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/adolph-reed-jr/marx_race_neoliberalism/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Sep 2023 02:47:39 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/adolph-reed-jr/marx_race_neoliberalism/</guid>
      <description>A Marxist perspective can be most helpful for understanding race and racism insofar as it per- ceives capitalism dialectically, as a social total- ity that includes modes of production, relations of production, and the pragmatically evolving ensemble of institutions and ideologies that lubricate and propel its reproduction. From this perspective, Marxism’s most important contri- bution to making sense of race and racism in the United States may be demystification. A histori- cal materialist perspective should stress that “race”—which includes “racism,” as one is unthinkable without the other—is a historically specific ideology that emerged, took shape, and has evolved as a constitutive element within a definite set of social relations anchored to a par- ticular system of production.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
