<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Class Letters</title><link>https://classletters.org/</link><description>Recent content on Class Letters</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 06:18:49 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://classletters.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Decision-Making in a Good Society: The Case for Nested Councils by Stephen R. Shalom</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/decision_making_postcap/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 06:18:49 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/decision_making_postcap/</guid><description>&lt;p>Stephen R. Shalom is emeritus professor of Political Science at William Paterson University of New Jersey, USA. He is a member of the editorial board
of New Politics, and a long-time activist in peace and justice movements.
Among other works, he is the author of &lt;em>Which Side Are You On? An Introduction
to Politics (Longman, 2003)&lt;/em>, &amp;ldquo;Parpolity: A Political System for a Good Society,&amp;rdquo;
in &lt;em>Real Utopia: Participatory Society for the 21st Century, ed. Chris Spannos, AK
Press, 2008)&lt;/em> and editor of &lt;em>Socialist Visions&lt;/em> (South End Press, 1983).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Weapon of Theory by Amilcar Cabral</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/cabral/weapon_of_theory/</link><pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2024 04:17:05 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/cabral/weapon_of_theory/</guid><description>&lt;p>Published in 1966. The text speaks for itself &amp;ndash; a terrific contextualisation of the National Liberation Movements.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>If any of us came to Cuba with doubts in our mind about the solidity, strength,
maturity and vitality of the Cuban Revolution, these doubts have been removed
by what we have been able to see. Our hearts are now warmed by an unshakeable
certainty which gives us courage in the difficult but glorious struggle against
the common enemy: no power in the world will be able to destroy this Cuban
Revolution, which is creating in the countryside and in the towns not only a
new life but also — and even more important — a New Man, fully conscious of his
national, continental and international rights and duties. In every field of
activity the Cuban people have made major progress during the last seven years,
particularly in 1965, Year of Agriculture.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>An Image of Africa: Racism in Conrad's Heart of Darkness by Chinua Achebe</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/achebe_conrad_hod/</link><pubDate>Sun, 22 Sep 2024 01:58:15 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/achebe_conrad_hod/</guid><description>&lt;p>In The Fall of 1974 I was walking one day from the English Department at the University of Massachusetts to a parking lot. It was a fine
autumn morning such as encouraged friendliness to passing strangers. Brisk
youngsters were hurrying in all directions, many of them obviously freshmen in their first flush of enthusiasm.An older man going the same way as I
turned and remarked to me how very young they came these days. I agreed.
Then he asked me if I was a student too. I said, no, I was a teacher.What did
I teach? African literature. Now that was funny, he said, because he knew a
fellow who taught the same thing, or perhaps it was African &lt;em>history&lt;/em>, in a certain community college not far from here. It always surprised him, he went
on to say, because he never had thought of Africa as having that kind of
stuff, you know. By this time I was walking much faster. “Oh well,” I heard
him say finally, behind me: “I guess I have to take your course to find out.”&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Seven Types of Obloquy: Traversties of Marxism by Norman Geras:</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/geras/seven_types/</link><pubDate>Sat, 29 Jun 2024 04:01:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/geras/seven_types/</guid><description>&lt;p>I see this as a terrific example of where reasoned and well formed criticism
can stand on its own, in spite of the divergent trajectory which the author
appears to take later on in his life through his reactionary offshoots.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As with any analytical field of inquiry which aspires to achieving insights, syntheses and increased understandings of the world, Marxism contains a broad array of unique and differeing perspectives, some of which fall far short of the high standard of rigor demanded of a scientific field. Here, Geras addresses several lazy and incongruent arguments put forward by Marxists who are themselves claiming to remedy pitfalls in Marx&amp;rsquo;s views; a public purging of sorts, these types of obloquy.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>About Class Letters</title><link>https://classletters.org/about/</link><pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2024 23:03:17 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/about/</guid><description>&lt;p>Class Letters seeks to be a regularly updated feed of articles, unified by the
goal of building a socialist~communist consciousness, itself thereafter seeking
a real body politic.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Alongside more clearly defined political and philosophical texts, Class Letters
incorporates works from different scientific, and health fields, bound by the
commitment that communist work can, and should be scientific. Without a doubt,
there is a purposeful goal of educating, and the goals of the autodidact are
encouraged &amp;ndash; we have a reverence for education and it&amp;rsquo;s transformative
potentials.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Capital Account Liberalization and the Developing Nations, an excerpt from José Antonio Ocampo</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/capital_account_liberalization/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2024 22:34:24 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/capital_account_liberalization/</guid><description>&lt;p>In looking to imagine and crystallise potential alternatives to the seemingly
unending vortex of underdevelopment and poverty in third and second world
nations, an understanding of the deficiencies and insufficiencies of the
current macroeconomic arrangement is an obvious starting point. The
post-Bretton Woods monetary consensus, which promised to guarantee mutual &amp;lsquo;real
growth&amp;rsquo; through endless liberalization of domestic markets and fluctuating exchange rates, has in whole been
failure for developing countries. Instead, of self-sufficiency and
self-confidence, there isn&amp;rsquo;t even what one one called &amp;lsquo;multi-lateral
beneficence&amp;rsquo;, but rather, a reliance and dependency on the most powerful players in the game, at the mercy of commodities swings and speculative exuberance
(rather than being &amp;rsquo;liberated&amp;rsquo; and domestically sound, buffered from &amp;lsquo;shocks&amp;rsquo;). One wonders what one
would do if they swapped shoes. What shall we do once we take control of these
responsibilities?&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Cancer Prevention and Screening by Jason Fung; The Cancer Code</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/public_health/cancer_code/cancer_code_pt2/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 23:41:44 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/public_health/cancer_code/cancer_code_pt2/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is part 2 of the post on Jason Fung&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;Cancer Code&amp;rsquo;. I found this a
remarkable case point in the iatrogenic potential of public health
interventions in which the effect on mortality is masked by a surrogate
of survival; early detection. When tracked for long enough time, early detection
does more harm than good, and thus, fails as a successful surrogate. You can
find part one
&lt;a href="https://classletters.org/posts/biology/public_health/cancer_code/">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I encourage everyone to read the entirety of Jason&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;The Cancer Code&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s a
terrific work of &amp;lsquo;popular&amp;rsquo; scientific writing, a story as much about
the biology of Cancer as it is about the sociology of biomedical practice and
research.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A False Dawn by Jason Fung; The Cancer Code</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/public_health/cancer_code/cancer_code/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Feb 2024 23:41:44 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/public_health/cancer_code/cancer_code/</guid><description>&lt;p>This post will be in two parts, both of which I find are illustrative of the
difficulties of public health strategies. One makes particularly obvious the
severe misanthropic consequences of profit seeking drives in the areas of
health and medicine, and the second is a remarkable case point in the
iatrogenic potential of public health interventions which may be completely
benevolent in intention &amp;ndash; something that all states irrespective of political
structure must address. Part one is contained below, you can find part two (here)[]&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Why no Roman Industrial Revolution? by Bret Devereaux</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/why_no_roman_ind_rev/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Feb 2024 23:20:45 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/why_no_roman_ind_rev/</guid><description>&lt;p>Original at &lt;a href="https://acoup.blog/2022/08/26/collections-why-no-roman-industrial-revolution/">https://acoup.blog/2022/08/26/collections-why-no-roman-industrial-revolution/&lt;/a> . Linked to it via Paul Cockshott.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-question">The Question&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>That said this is a question that is not absurd a priori. As we’ll see, the
Roman Empire was never close to an industrial revolution – a great many of the
preconditions were missing – but the idea that it might have been on the cusp
of being something like a modern economy did once have its day in the
scholarship. As I’ve mentioned before, the dominant feature of the historical
debate among scholars about the shape of the Roman economy is between
‘modernists’ who argue the Roman economy is relatively more like a modern
economy (meaning both that it was relatively more prosperous than other ancient
economies but also that the Romans themselves maintained a more modern,
familiar outlook towards money, investment and production) and ‘primitivsts’
who argue that actually the Roman economy was quite primitive, less prosperous
and with the Romans themselves holding attitudes about the economy quite alien
to our own. But here we need to get into a bit more specificity because beneath
that quick description it is necessary to separate what we might call the ‘old
modernists’ and the ‘new modernists.’&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Darwin's Delay by Stephen Jay Gould</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/sjgould/darwins_delay/</link><pubDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2024 23:28:27 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/sjgould/darwins_delay/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="darwins-delay">Darwin&amp;rsquo;s Delay&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Few events inspire more speculation than long and unexplained pauses in the activities of
famous people. Rossini crowned a brilliant operatic career with William Tell and then wrote
almost nothing for the next thirty-five years. Dorothy Sayers abandoned Lord Peter Wimsey
at the height of his popularity and turned instead to God. Charles Darwin developed a radical
theory of evolution in 1838 and published it twenty-one years later only because A. R.
Wallace was about to scoop him.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Studies in European Realism by György Lukács</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/lukacs/studies_in_european_realism/</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2023 02:07:16 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/lukacs/studies_in_european_realism/</guid><description>&lt;p>The articles contained in this book were written some ten years ago. Author and reader
may well ask why they should be republished just now. At first sight they might seem to
lack all topicality. Subject and tone alike may appear remote to a considerable section of
public opinion. I believe, however, that they have some topicality in that, without
entering upon any detailed polemics, they represent a point of view in opposition to
certain literary and philosophical trends still very much to the fore today.
Let us begin with the general atmosphere: the clouds of mysticism which once
surrounded the phenomena of literature with a poetic colour and warmth and created
an intimate and ‘‘interesting’’ atmosphere around them, have been dispersed. Things
now face us in a clear, sharp light which to many may seem cold and hard; a light shed
on them by the teachings of Marx. Marxism searches for the material roots of each
phenomenon, regards them in their historical connections and movement, ascertains the
laws of such movement and demonstrates their development from root to flower, and in
so doing lifts every phenomenon out of a merely emotional, irrational, mystic fog and
brings it to the bright light of understanding.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Marx, Race and Neoliberalism by Adolph Reed Jr.</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/adolph-reed-jr/marx_race_neoliberalism/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 Sep 2023 02:47:39 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/adolph-reed-jr/marx_race_neoliberalism/</guid><description>&lt;p>A Marxist perspective can be most helpful for understanding race and racism
insofar as it per- ceives capitalism dialectically, as a social total- ity that
includes modes of production, relations of production, and the pragmatically
evolving ensemble of institutions and ideologies that lubricate and propel its
reproduction. From this perspective, Marxism’s most important contri- bution to
making sense of race and racism in the United States may be demystification. A
histori- cal materialist perspective should stress that “race”—which includes
“racism,” as one is unthinkable without the other—is a historically specific
ideology that emerged, took shape, and has evolved as a constitutive element
within a definite set of social relations anchored to a par- ticular system of
production.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Revolutionary Medicine by Ernesto Che Guevara</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/revolutionarey_medicine_che/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Aug 2023 07:31:37 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/revolutionarey_medicine_che/</guid><description>&lt;p>Adapted from &lt;a href="https://www.marxists.org/archive/guevara/1960/08/19.htm">https://www.marxists.org/archive/guevara/1960/08/19.htm&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I was put onto this article from the reading of the terrific
text on the Cuban and Venezuelan healthcare systems and practices by Steven
Brouwer: &lt;a href="https://monthlyreview.org/product/revolutionary_doctors/">&amp;ldquo;Revolutionary Doctors: How Venezuela and Cuba Are Changing the World’s
Conception of Health Care&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This simple celebration, another among the hundreds of public functions with
which the Cuban people daily celebrate their liberty, the progress of all their
revolutionary laws, and their advances along the road to complete independence,
is of special interest to me.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Cuacasians Only: an excerpt from Robert Fogelson</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/suburbia/cuacasians_only/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Jul 2023 07:18:50 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/suburbia/cuacasians_only/</guid><description>&lt;p>A small but very important subsection from Robert Fogelson&amp;rsquo;s book &amp;ldquo;Bourgeois
Nightmares: Suburbia, 1870-1930&amp;rdquo;. I would say it speaks for itself.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Many subdividers also employed restrictions to exclude
‘‘undesirable’’ people as well as &amp;ldquo;undesirable&amp;rdquo; activities. By far the
most common of these provisions were racial covenants. Under
a typical covenant, an owner was forbidden to sell or lease the
property to a member of any of a number of allegedly undesirable
racial, ethnic, or religious groups. He or she was also forbidden
to allow a member of these groups, other than chauffeurs, gardeners, or domestic servants, to use or occupy the property. A few
subdividers had employed racial covenants in the mid-nineteenth
century. In Brookline, for example, one forbade &amp;ldquo;any negro or
native of Ireland&amp;rdquo; to occupy a dwelling, and in Baltimore another
barred the sale or lease of a house to &amp;ldquo;a negro or person of African
or Mongolian [that is, Asian] descent.&amp;rdquo; But such restrictions were
very much the exception before the 1890s. Indeed, not even the
most racist subdividers imposed racial covenants. A case in point
was Francis G. Newlands, the mining magnate and U.S. senator
who laid out Chevy Chase in the early 1890s. Newlands saw the
United States as &amp;ldquo;the home of the white race.&amp;rdquo; To him, &amp;ldquo;race tolerance&amp;rdquo; meant &amp;ldquo;race amalgamation,&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;race intolerance&amp;rdquo; meant
&amp;ldquo;race war.&amp;rdquo; Fusing the racism of the South with the racism of the
West, he called for repealing the Fifteenth Amendment, thereby
denying African-Americans, &amp;ldquo;an inferior race,&amp;rdquo; the right to vote,
and restricting immigration to &amp;ldquo;the white race,&amp;rdquo; thereby excluding Chinese, Japanese, and other Asians. Despite his outspoken racism, Newlands did not include racial covenants among the
minimum cost requirements and other restrictions he imposed
on the first subdivisions at Chevy Chase.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Conclusion to the Gift by Marcel Mauss</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/marcel-mauss/conclusion-to-the-gift/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jun 2023 05:03:51 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/marcel-mauss/conclusion-to-the-gift/</guid><description>&lt;p>The conclusion to Mauss&amp;rsquo;s incredible essay on the uses and concepts of gifts.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="moral-conclusions">Moral Conclusions&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>It is possible to extend these observations to our own
societies. A considerable part of our morality and our lives
themselves are still permeated with this same atmosphere of
the gift, where obligation and liberty intermingle. Fortunately,
everything is still not wholly categorized in terms of buying
and selling. Things still have sentimental as well as venal value,
assuming values merely of this kind exist. We possess more
than a tradesman morality. There still remain people and
classes that keep to the morality of former times, and we
almost all observe it, at least at certain times of the year or
on certain occasions.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Socialism or Moralism by Bayard Rustin</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/socialism-or-moralism_rustin/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 03:30:51 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/socialism-or-moralism_rustin/</guid><description>&lt;p>Cross posted from &lt;a href="https://nonsite.org/socialism-or-moralism/">Nonsite.org&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Passages between brackets are drawn from the manuscript version of the essay and differ slightly from the published variant.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Published July 7, 1970&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We on the democratic left are living through a real crisis. And precisely
because I believe the Socialist Party has a very vital role to play in this
period, I would like to say something about the problems we confront.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One aspect is that many people on the [so-called democratic] left today
substitute psychology for politics. Now, I have no objection to a lifestyle, or
how you wear your hair, or whether you eat pig’s feet[, or whether you want to
dress so one cannot distinguish between male and female except upon very close
inspection]. But to substitute this “how I feel, what my thing is,” for
politics, is an extremely dangerous attitude which the Socialist movement must
fight. In fact, the Socialist movement is one of the few movements which has the
credentials for fighting it.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Introduction: Restoration in Russia by Boris Kagarlitsky</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/restoration-in-russia/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 May 2023 02:35:24 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/restoration-in-russia/</guid><description>&lt;p>This brief writing belongs to the Introduction to Boris Kagarlitsky&amp;rsquo;s book
&amp;ldquo;Restoration in Russia: Why Capitalism Failed&amp;rdquo;. The work is both a valuable
reflection of, and look into, the tumultuous years following the dissolution of
the USSR.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;lsquo;You can&amp;rsquo;t hammer in a bolt.&amp;rsquo; This was among the slogans used by the
pro-government political bloc Russia&amp;rsquo;s Choice in its campaign for the
parliamentary elections of December 1993. Spokespeople for the bloc explained
to voters: it&amp;rsquo;s pointless to dream of a just society, so you have to reconcile
yourself to the new order. The slogan turned out to be unintentionally ironic.
The attempts by Yelstin, Gaidar and the other Russian &amp;lsquo;reformers&amp;rsquo; to construct
liberal capitalism in a country where there is neither a normal bourgeoise, nor
a market infrastructure, were a case of &amp;lsquo;hammering a bolt&amp;rsquo;.&lt;br>
History is being repeated as farce. This might not sound very original, but it
is nevertheless true. The developments in Russia during the early 1990s have
been frightening, but at the same time comic. Highly organized political groups
engage in battles without rules in an unstable society where interests are ill
defined. One can speak of class conflict only with reservations. The fights
inside the government are reminiscent of a squabble in a sandpit. &lt;br>
Psychology plays as big a role here as economics. The instability of social
structures, the destruction of former institutions and the crisis of traditions
have all helped to make social psychology so important a factor. This applies
equally to the country&amp;rsquo;s rulers, to the opposition and to the millions of
citizens living in territories whose names and borders are uncertain, and which
no one is yet in a position to rename. These are territories which, despite
everything, are still known as the &amp;lsquo;former Soviet Union&amp;rsquo;. &lt;br>
The dizzying changes began with the elections of 1990. Prior to this everything
had taken place within a more of less predictable scenario of &amp;lsquo;managed reform&amp;rsquo;.
The Communist Party was gradually relaxing its control, while not allowing
power to slip from its hands. Gorbachev, with full support from the West, was
preparing to transform himself from general secretary of the party into
president, with unlimited powers. Not the party forums where the necessity of
reforms was proclaimed in the late 1980s, nor the conflict between Yeltsin and
Gorbachev, nor the discussions in the all-union Congress of Peoples&amp;rsquo; Deputies,
nor even mass opposition demonstrations and miner&amp;rsquo;s strikes had as yet
testified to the disintegration of the state. But it was already clear that the
reformers were losing control of the situation. Their own decisions had called
new social forces into being, and these forces were finding the context of the
Soviet state constricting. &lt;br>
The 1990 elections became a turning-point. In all the republics indigenous
authorities, independent of Moscow, made their appearance. The local
bureaucracies, which until this time has been doomed to play a secondary role,
gained in self-confidence. Regional and republican-level functionaries did not
in most cases stand for election, did not campaign for electors&amp;rsquo; votes, and did
not debate with rival candidates at meetings, but nevertheless they were the
main victors. The numerous popularly elected representatives were their
hostages. In order to exercise real power in defiance of the wishes of the
union centre, the deputies had to rest on the local apparatus. The ideologue of
reform Gavriil Popov called this &amp;rsquo;the bloc of democrats with the apparatus&amp;rsquo;.
One way or another, the change took place; from being the leader of the
reforms, controlling the situation in the country, Gorbachev was quickly
transformed into a commander without an army. People who only recently had been
his supporters now abandoned him, while his Western friends prepared to support
Yeltsin as the &amp;rsquo;new Russian leader&amp;rsquo;.&lt;br>
Repeating the experience of Gorbachev, Yeltsin had himself elected president of
Russia. Lesser figures contended themselves with positions as mayors. Every
boss at each particular level sought to grab as much power as possible from the
centre. At the same time, these bosses were forced to struggle against rivals
from below, also seeking their scrap of power. All of them, however, had one
thing in common: despite talking about democracy and freedom, they had no
intention of giving the majority of citizens any access whatever to the levels
of authority. &lt;br>
In August 1991 all this came to and end. An attempt by the
Union level Soviet bureaucrats to change the relationship of forces in their
favour led to the creation of the State Committee on the Emergency Situation,
whose demise was readily predictable. The members of the committee were
declared to be &amp;lsquo;putschists&amp;rsquo;. By taking his distance from them, Gorbachev
managed to keep his post for a few more months, but already in August he was a
political corpse.&lt;br>
Now, finally, a degree of certainty appeared. People were in power who had made
a simple, final choice in favour of the West. They chose freedom for
themselves, and were ready to defend it against all encroachments. This meant
that there were no longer willing to be restricted either by the framework of
the law, or by generally recognized institutions. Still less were they prepared
to take into account the wishes of the majority of the hungry and confused
population. &lt;br>
The period which followed saw all institutional structures systematically
destroyed. In December 1991, by agreement of the presidents of three republics,
the Soviet Union was abolished at Belovezhskaya Pushcha. The Communist Party was
abolished. Then it was resurrected, banned, again revived, once more banned and
then once again legalized. But this was now a different organization, with
different members and goals. The Komsomol vanished more or less of its own
accord, with its activists calmly crossing over into commercial organizations.
The armed forces began to be split up. &lt;br>
Now it was the turn of the soviets and of the enterprises of the state sector.
The &amp;lsquo;property of all the people&amp;rsquo; was turned into a boundless reservoir of funds
for personal enrichment. The soviets, which has brought Yeltsin to power, were
declared to be relics of totalitarianism. However, these structures were not
simply elements of the state system. They were part of the accustomed way of
life, not just deciding political and economic questions, but also dealing with
a multitude of social and even cultural tasks. They dealt with these tasks after
their own fashion &amp;mdash; vulgarly and inefficiently. But now people discovered that
no one was going to deal with these tasks at all. &lt;br>
Before long, many of the people who in the autumn of 1991 had welcomed the
dismembering of the USSR wound up in opposition. Some were reacting to the
growth of dissatisfaction among voters, others had experienced an awakening of
conscience, and still others were distributed by the collapse of structures that
were no longer those of the USSR, but Russian, and hence their own. Thus
Vice-President Aleksandr Rutskoi and speaker of the Russian parliament Ruslan
Khasbulatov were transformed from comrades-in-arms of Yeltsin in his mortal
enemies. &lt;br>
The resistance from the soviets was not broken immediately. In December 1992
Yeltsin threatened to disband the Supreme Soviet, but did not carry out this
threat. Then he tried to introduce &amp;lsquo;special rule&amp;rsquo;, but again retreated. The
first test of strength became the referendum forced on the country by the
authorities in April 1993. This was conducted in conditions that included harsh
censorship of television broadcasts and a degree of manipulation of public
opinion that was unprecedented even by Soviet standards. The referendum yielded
ambiguous results; a third of the population did not vote, and the demand for
early election of deputies failed to pass. But the regime was now able to refer
to the trust expressed by the population in the president. &lt;br>
The voting in April was a prelude to the bloodshed in October. Throughout 1993
the authorities were preoccupied with only one question: how to rid themselves
of the deputies, the laws and the Constitutional Court, all of which were
restriction the regime in the exercise of its free initiative. In September the
denouement began. First the militia beat people on the streets, and then tanks
opened fire on the parliament building. &lt;br>
Securing the victory required free elections and a new constitution,
guaranteeing the president and his team complete freedom from responsibility,
and most important, enshrining the rights of the new property-owners.&lt;br>
On 12 December 1993 the elections went ahead, despite chaos in the Central
Electoral Commission and constant breaches of deadlines and rules. The result,
to use the language of advertising, was beyond all expectations. Half the
population failed to vote, and of those who turned up at the polling stations,
the overwhelming majority gave their votes to opponents of the regime.&lt;br>
The authorities had spared neither money nor energies in organizing a &amp;rsquo;triumph
of democracy&amp;rsquo;. Sociological research for the organizing a &amp;rsquo;triumph of
democracy&amp;rsquo;. Sociological research for the pro-government Russia&amp;rsquo;s Choice blog
was paid for out of state funds. The voter lists in Moscow included dead people,
and residents of long-vacant buildings. By a wondrous coincidence, large numbers
of such &amp;lsquo;voters&amp;rsquo; were recorded as living in a building once inhabited by
Nikolay Gogol, author of the classic nineteenth-century novel &lt;em>Dead Souls&lt;/em>. One
of the heads of the district electoral commissions in Moscow hanged himself the
night before voting, after writing in a last message to his relatives, &amp;lsquo;My dear
ones, I have deceived people so grievously that there is no forgiveness for me.&amp;rsquo; &lt;br>
In St Petersburg, opposition activists who were gathering petition signatures on
the streets were confronted by heavily built young men travelling about the city
in second-hand Volvos. According to journalists, this squad chased petitioners
out of metro stations, seized and tore up petition sheets, and handed out very
professional beatings to the most obstinate signature-gatherers. People
collecting signatures for pro-government candidates were for some reason not
touched. &lt;br>
When ballot boxes were opened in Voronezh, south of Moscow, electoral officials
discovered a third more ballot papers than had been handed out to voters.
Soldiers were herded into the polling stations in whole units, without even
being asked whether they wanted to vote. Scrutineers for opposition candidates
were not allowed to be present when votes were counted. Hundreds of such cases
were noted throughout the country, and were reported in the press and even on
television. Only the foreign observers tried not to notice anything, and even
refused to travel to places where breaches had been discovered. &lt;br>
In the Kremlin on the night of 12-13 December, a televised extravaganza had been
organized to welcome in the new political epoch. Yeltsin and Gaidar were
supposed to take part. The &amp;lsquo;independent&amp;rsquo; television programme &lt;em>Itogi&lt;/em>, which
even on the censored airwaves of Russia was distinguished by its servility, had
already announced the success of Russia&amp;rsquo;s Choice. Alas, the triumph did not come
to pass. Around half the voters did not go to the polls. Russian Movement for
Democratic Reforms, the grouping closest to Russia&amp;rsquo;s Choice, failed to attract
the 5 per cent of votes needed for the majority of soldiers and junior officers
voted for the opposition. This was also true of the units which had taken part
in the storming of the parliament. &lt;br>
It is possible to fool people for a long time. It is possible to turn the whole
country into a laboratory for fascinating experiments, and its residents into
guinea-pigs. But sooner or later the truth emerges that the freedom of the
authorities is not unlimited. At that point millions of people realize, on the
basis of their own tormented experience, that the less freedom the authorities
enjoy, the more there is for the citizens.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Global Neoliberal Practice: Institutions and Regulation in Africa by Graham Harrison</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/neoliberal-africa-global-practice/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2023 22:51:40 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/neoliberal-africa-global-practice/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is a chapter out of Graham Harrison&amp;rsquo;s Book &amp;ldquo;Neoliberal Africa: The Impact
of Global Social Engineering&amp;rdquo;. Although the book is more of an essay containing
fragmentary thoughts, I found this chapter substantial in the sense that it
clearly outlined the various institutional avenues in which projects such as
neoliberalism cement their ideology.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>This chapter considers the global emergence of neoliberalism. It looks at the
ways in which neoliberal practice has emerged, expanded and established for
itself ‘paradigmatic’ status. In other words, it shows how neoliberalism has
shifted from an ambitious and embryonic set of policy interventions to
something resembling a framework or set of premisses within which policy is
articulated. The practices of neoliberalism have been iterated over such time
as to shift the habits, conduct and repertoire of development practice tout
court. The layering of large numbers of neoliberal policies has not only led to
a progressively more totalising implementation of liberalisation; it has also
defined the terms upon which policy and development are thought about and
articulated per se. This is, of course, not a completed process (in the last
chapter we developed a framework which is anathema to the idea of completed
processes, preferring instead a series of practices in place of means–ends
distinctions), but it has enabled neoliberal ideas to aspire to
‘meta-development’ status: that is, as the terms upon which development is
discussed rather than solely as a predominant model of development. At the
level of ideas, this shift or tendency is rather like the analysis of Hay in
which neoliberalism moves from normalising to normative (Hay 2004).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Race into Culture: A Critical Genealogy of Cultural Identity by Walter Benn Michaels</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/walter-benn-michaels/geneology-race-into-culture/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Mar 2023 10:59:16 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/walter-benn-michaels/geneology-race-into-culture/</guid><description>&lt;p>Due to the prolific number of footnotes that Michael&amp;rsquo;s article contains, the
essay will simply be linked to here. It is an important walk through the
trajectories that various essentialist concepts have taken in the course of modern
Northern American history. What surprised me most was this quasi-progess &amp;mdash; where
it appears that the concept of race has been disposed of, it&amp;rsquo;s kernel is
carried over into a different, yet sadly, familial form.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Soviet Literature by Maxim Gorky</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/maxim-gorky/soviet-literature/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 08:06:39 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/maxim-gorky/soviet-literature/</guid><description>&lt;p>Herein is a speech delivered in August 1934, and published in 1935. It reappeared
in Gorky, Radek, Bukharin, Zhdanov and others “Soviet Writers’ Congress 1934,”
page 25-69, Lawrence &amp;amp; Wishart, 1977, and was transcribed by Jose Braz for the
Marxists Internet Archive.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>The role of the labour processes, which have converted a two-Legged animal into
man and created the basic elements of culture, has never been investigated as
deeply and thoroughly as it deserves. This is quite natural, for such research
would not be in the interests of the exploiters of labour. The latter, who use
the energy of the masses as a sort of raw material to be turned into money,
could not, of course, enhance the value of this raw material. Ever since remote
antiquity, when mankind was divided into slaves and slave-owners, they have
used the vital power of the toiling mass in the same way as we today use the
mechanical force of river currents. Primitive man has been depicted by the
historians of culture as a philosophizing idealist and mystic, a creator of
gods, a seeker after &lt;em>“the meaning of life.”&lt;/em> Primitive man has been saddled with
the mentality of a Jacob Böhme, a cobbler who lived at the end of the sixteenth
and the beginning of the seventeenth century and who occupied himself between
whiles with philosophy of a kind extremely popular among bourgeois mystics;
Böhme preached that &lt;em>“Man should meditate on the Skies, on the Stars and the
Elements, and on the Creatures which do proceed from them, and likewise on the
Holy Angels, the Devil, Heaven and Hell.&amp;quot;&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Crisis of Bourgeois Philosophy by György Lukács</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/lukacs/crisis-of-bourgeois-philosophy/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Mar 2023 01:59:10 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/lukacs/crisis-of-bourgeois-philosophy/</guid><description>&lt;p>Written in 1948.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The fact of the crisis has been stated not only by us Marxists. The concept of
“crisis” has long taken root in bourgeois philosophy. When, for example,
Siegfried Marck, a famous neo-Hegelian, wanted to define Rickert’s place in the
development of philosophy, he called him a thinker of the “pre-crisis era.”
Indeed, if we carefully trace the development of bourgeois philosophy in recent
decades, we will see that literally every two years the foundations of
philosophy are again and again called into question. It is no coincidence that
this development was initiated by Nietzsche’s program: a reassessment of all
values. This continues endlessly in modern philosophy; a year during which a
crisis did not break out in some area of philosophy is a year without any
events.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Introduction to Class Notes by Adolph Reed Jr.</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/adolph-reed-jr/intro-to-class-notes/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2023 02:15:15 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/adolph-reed-jr/intro-to-class-notes/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>The text here is an extract from Adolph Reed Jr&amp;rsquo;s 2000 work &amp;ldquo;Class Notes&amp;rdquo;. This publication is the founding inspiration for the theme and title of this site here &amp;ndash; long live Reed.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This book is built on commentary about current issues and events in american
politics over most of the 1990s. as such, it expresses an on-going attempt to
make sense of contemporary american political life from a critical perspective.
most of the essays published here appeared originally in substantially the same
form in my regular columns in the progressive and the village voice, or in
similar venues. writing in those venues presents a special challenge— to convey
complex, perhaps unconventional ideas clearly and concisely to a general
audience. i’ve found this challenge very useful partly because i work out my
own views on many issues by writing about them; to that extent, these essays
are much less a set of didactic pronoucements than a sustained attempt to think
things through, and the obligation to communicate those views effectively to
others encourages preciseness and clarity. having to ask constantly, “what
would this formulation mean to someone outside my own head or outside a
narrowly specialized community of discourse?” imposes a requirement to bring
abstractions down to the ground, to imagine how— if at all— they appear in,
explain or bear upon the daily world we inhabit and reproduce. the challenge
is more important, though, as a corrective to the flight from concreteness that
has increasingly beset left theorizing and social criticism, and as a result
political practice, in the u.s. in recent decades.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>