<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Class Letters</title><link>https://classletters.org/</link><description>Recent content on Class Letters</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 May 2025 06:20:02 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://classletters.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Chile, an Investigation of Aid as Imperialism by Teresa Hayter</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/aid_as_imperialism_chile/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 May 2025 06:20:02 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/aid_as_imperialism_chile/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Teresa Hayter&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;Aid as Imperialism&amp;rsquo;, was one of the first somewhat critical
texts written about the post world-war II monetary institutions, from a so
called insider&amp;rsquo;s view. Having spent some time employed at the Overseas
Development Institute, the World Bank financed Teresa&amp;rsquo;s research on the
effectiveness of aid packages provided to Third World countries. Given it was
intended as a publication on behalf of the ODI, one certainly encounters a
report which offers an objective overview of the various policy approaches that
these institutions taken. The first half of the text, is an outline, not a
critique. The second half turns to evaluating the implementation of these
approaches in several countries. Here is where we find a critical evaluation,
which best portrays the inflexibility of foreign aid packages, which, Teresa
believed, were given more so as blanket prescriptions, dogmas even. A standard
buffet of currency devaluations and austerity measures &amp;mdash; liberalize,
liberalize, liberalize! It is for this reason that the Overseas Development
Institute rejected the original report for publication. Fortunately, it
eventually made it&amp;rsquo;s way to us common readers. The following is an excerpt from the
text, focusing on the involvement of these aid agencies in Chile, a country which is emblematic of the deep difficulties of modernization and sovereignty in the global periphery.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Theory of the Innovative Organization by William Lazonick</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/lazonick/theory_of_innovative_organization/</link><pubDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2025 21:52:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/lazonick/theory_of_innovative_organization/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;An excerpt from William Lazonick&amp;rsquo;s terrific work &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Business Organization and the
Myth of the Market Economy&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;, a book that offers a critique of what a &amp;lsquo;market
economy&amp;rsquo; is purported to be, through an evaluation of the strategies and
economic histories of businesses within what can be called &amp;ldquo;actually existing
capitalism&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, at the risk of a small amount of
repetition, I shall supplement that discussion by focusing on the nature
of fixed costs, the different sources of uncertainty the innovative organization faces, and the relation between organizational capability and technological change.
Through its investment activities, a business organization commits financial resources to specific processes to make particular products with
the expectation of reaping financial returns. Once they are committed,
the productive assets of the organization represent fixed costs that must
then be recouped by the production and sale of output. If, through the
sale of sufficient output, investments could generate expected financial
returns instantaneously, fixed costs would not represent an economic
problem to the organization. But then, we would probably not call the
“assets” underlying these costs “investments.” Indeed, we might not even
deem it appropriate to call these costs “fixed” or the entity that incurs
them a firm. The problem of fixed costs occurs because the production
and sale of the enterprise’s output occur neither instantaneously nor with
certainty. The basic economic problem that confronts the capitalist enterprise is to transform fixed costs into revenue-generating products to realize financial returns. An analysis of how and with what success the business organization manages this transformation is the key to understanding
technological change, value creation, and economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The 'Lethal Chamber' in Eugenic Thought: an excerpt from Breeding Superman: Nietzsche, Race and Eugenics in Edwardian and Interwar Britain by Dan Stone</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/nietzsche/breeding-superman-eugenics/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2025 01:51:19 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/nietzsche/breeding-superman-eugenics/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Chapter five from &lt;em&gt;Breeding Superman: Nietzsche, Race and Eugenics in Edwardian and Interwar Britain&lt;/em&gt; by Dan Stone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we have seen, before the First World War, and in some circles until well
into the interwar period, eugenics &amp;mdash; literally, ‘well born’ or ‘good stocks’&amp;mdash; was the height of sophisticated, ‘progressive’ thought.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Across Europe, the
novels and plays of the period, such as H. G. Wells’s &lt;em&gt;The New Machiavelli&lt;/em&gt;
(1911) and George Bernard Shaw’s &lt;em&gt;Man and Superman&lt;/em&gt; (1905), are suffused
with the language of race-regeneration and fears of physical deterioration. In
Arthur Schnitzler’s novel, &lt;em&gt;The Road to the Open&lt;/em&gt; (1908), Berthold Stauber, a
young and enthusiastic Viennese Jewish physician, tells his father, the
humane Dr Stauber, that ‘You need only consider, father, that the most
honest and consistent social hygiene would have the direct result of annihilating diseased people, or at any rate excluding them from all enjoyment of
life, and I don’t deny that I have all kinds of ideas tending in that way which
may seem cruel at the first glance.’ He went on to say that ‘You needn’t be
afraid, father, that I shall begin straight away to preach the murder of the
unhealthy and superfluous. But theoretically that’s certainly what my programme leads to.’&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Although primarily a conservative ideology, both left and
right were attracted to eugenic proposals. These ranged from ‘positive’ measures such as the encouragement of ‘hygienic marriage’, that is, marriage
between two people of good stock, to ‘negative’ measures such as sterilisation or segregation in order to ensure that the unfit, feeble-minded and
morally degenerate did not have children. In this chapter I will consider
eugenics in general, before concentrating on one aspect of its rhetoric which
to a post-Second World War audience is perhaps even more shocking than it
was to an Edwardian one.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Decision-Making in a Good Society: The Case for Nested Councils by Stephen R. Shalom</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/decision_making/decision_making_postcap/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 06:18:49 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/decision_making/decision_making_postcap/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Stephen R. Shalom is emeritus professor of Political Science at William Paterson University of New Jersey, USA. He is a member of the editorial board
of New Politics, and a long-time activist in peace and justice movements.
Among other works, he is the author of &lt;em&gt;Which Side Are You On? An Introduction
to Politics (Longman, 2003)&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;ldquo;Parpolity: A Political System for a Good Society,&amp;rdquo;
in &lt;em&gt;Real Utopia: Participatory Society for the 21st Century, ed. Chris Spannos, AK
Press, 2008)&lt;/em&gt; and editor of &lt;em&gt;Socialist Visions&lt;/em&gt; (South End Press, 1983).&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Weapon of Theory by Amilcar Cabral</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/cabral/weapon_of_theory/</link><pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2024 04:17:05 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/cabral/weapon_of_theory/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Published in 1966. The text speaks for itself &amp;ndash; a terrific contextualisation of the National Liberation Movements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If any of us came to Cuba with doubts in our mind about the solidity, strength,
maturity and vitality of the Cuban Revolution, these doubts have been removed
by what we have been able to see. Our hearts are now warmed by an unshakeable
certainty which gives us courage in the difficult but glorious struggle against
the common enemy: no power in the world will be able to destroy this Cuban
Revolution, which is creating in the countryside and in the towns not only a
new life but also — and even more important — a New Man, fully conscious of his
national, continental and international rights and duties. In every field of
activity the Cuban people have made major progress during the last seven years,
particularly in 1965, Year of Agriculture.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>An Image of Africa: Racism in Conrad's Heart of Darkness by Chinua Achebe</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/achebe_conrad_hod/</link><pubDate>Sun, 22 Sep 2024 01:58:15 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/achebe_conrad_hod/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In The Fall of 1974 I was walking one day from the English Department at the University of Massachusetts to a parking lot. It was a fine
autumn morning such as encouraged friendliness to passing strangers. Brisk
youngsters were hurrying in all directions, many of them obviously freshmen in their first flush of enthusiasm.An older man going the same way as I
turned and remarked to me how very young they came these days. I agreed.
Then he asked me if I was a student too. I said, no, I was a teacher.What did
I teach? African literature. Now that was funny, he said, because he knew a
fellow who taught the same thing, or perhaps it was African &lt;em&gt;history&lt;/em&gt;, in a certain community college not far from here. It always surprised him, he went
on to say, because he never had thought of Africa as having that kind of
stuff, you know. By this time I was walking much faster. “Oh well,” I heard
him say finally, behind me: “I guess I have to take your course to find out.”&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Seven Types of Obloquy: Traversties of Marxism by Norman Geras:</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/geras/seven_types/</link><pubDate>Sat, 29 Jun 2024 04:01:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/geras/seven_types/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I see this as a terrific example of where reasoned and well formed criticism
can stand on its own, in spite of the divergent trajectory which the author
appears to take later on in his life through his reactionary offshoots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with any analytical field of inquiry which aspires to achieving insights, syntheses and increased understandings of the world, Marxism contains a broad array of unique and differeing perspectives, some of which fall far short of the high standard of rigor demanded of a scientific field. Here, Geras addresses several lazy and incongruent arguments put forward by Marxists who are themselves claiming to remedy pitfalls in Marx&amp;rsquo;s views; a public purging of sorts, these types of obloquy.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>About Class Letters</title><link>https://classletters.org/about/</link><pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2024 23:03:17 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/about/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Class Letters seeks to be a regularly updated feed of articles, unified by the
goal of building a socialist~communist consciousness, itself thereafter seeking
a real body politic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alongside more clearly defined political and philosophical texts, Class Letters
incorporates works from different scientific, and health fields, bound by the
commitment that communist work can, and should be scientific. Without a doubt,
there is a purposeful goal of educating, and the goals of the autodidact are
encouraged &amp;ndash; we have a reverence for education and it&amp;rsquo;s transformative
potentials.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Capital Account Liberalization and the Developing Nations, an excerpt from José Antonio Ocampo</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/capital_account_liberalization/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2024 22:34:24 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/capital_account_liberalization/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In looking to imagine and crystallise potential alternatives to the seemingly
unending vortex of underdevelopment and poverty in third and second world
nations, an understanding of the deficiencies and insufficiencies of the
current macroeconomic arrangement is an obvious starting point. The
post-Bretton Woods monetary consensus, which promised to guarantee mutual &amp;lsquo;real
growth&amp;rsquo; through endless liberalization of domestic markets and fluctuating exchange rates, has in whole been
failure for developing countries. Instead, of self-sufficiency and
self-confidence, there isn&amp;rsquo;t even what one one called &amp;lsquo;multi-lateral
beneficence&amp;rsquo;, but rather, a reliance and dependency on the most powerful players in the game, at the mercy of commodities swings and speculative exuberance
(rather than being &amp;rsquo;liberated&amp;rsquo; and domestically sound, buffered from &amp;lsquo;shocks&amp;rsquo;). One wonders what one
would do if they swapped shoes. What shall we do once we take control of these
responsibilities?&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Cancer Prevention and Screening by Jason Fung; The Cancer Code</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/public_health/cancer_code/cancer_code_pt2/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 23:41:44 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/public_health/cancer_code/cancer_code_pt2/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This is part 2 of the post on Jason Fung&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;Cancer Code&amp;rsquo;. I found this a
remarkable case point in the iatrogenic potential of public health
interventions in which the effect on mortality is masked by a surrogate
of survival; early detection. When tracked for long enough time, early detection
does more harm than good, and thus, fails as a successful surrogate. You can
find part one
&lt;a href="https://classletters.org/posts/biology/public_health/cancer_code/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I encourage everyone to read the entirety of Jason&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;The Cancer Code&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s a
terrific work of &amp;lsquo;popular&amp;rsquo; scientific writing, a story as much about
the biology of Cancer as it is about the sociology of biomedical practice and
research.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>A False Dawn by Jason Fung; The Cancer Code</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/public_health/cancer_code/cancer_code/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Feb 2024 23:41:44 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/public_health/cancer_code/cancer_code/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This post will be in two parts, both of which I find are illustrative of the
difficulties of public health strategies. One makes particularly obvious the
severe misanthropic consequences of profit seeking drives in the areas of
health and medicine, and the second is a remarkable case point in the
iatrogenic potential of public health interventions which may be completely
benevolent in intention &amp;ndash; something that all states irrespective of political
structure must address. Part one is contained below, you can find part two (here)[]&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Why no Roman Industrial Revolution? by Bret Devereaux</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/why_no_roman_ind_rev/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Feb 2024 23:20:45 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/why_no_roman_ind_rev/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Original at &lt;a href="https://acoup.blog/2022/08/26/collections-why-no-roman-industrial-revolution/"&gt;https://acoup.blog/2022/08/26/collections-why-no-roman-industrial-revolution/&lt;/a&gt; . Linked to it via Paul Cockshott.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-question"&gt;The Question&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said this is a question that is not absurd a priori. As we’ll see, the
Roman Empire was never close to an industrial revolution – a great many of the
preconditions were missing – but the idea that it might have been on the cusp
of being something like a modern economy did once have its day in the
scholarship. As I’ve mentioned before, the dominant feature of the historical
debate among scholars about the shape of the Roman economy is between
‘modernists’ who argue the Roman economy is relatively more like a modern
economy (meaning both that it was relatively more prosperous than other ancient
economies but also that the Romans themselves maintained a more modern,
familiar outlook towards money, investment and production) and ‘primitivsts’
who argue that actually the Roman economy was quite primitive, less prosperous
and with the Romans themselves holding attitudes about the economy quite alien
to our own. But here we need to get into a bit more specificity because beneath
that quick description it is necessary to separate what we might call the ‘old
modernists’ and the ‘new modernists.’&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Darwin's Delay by Stephen Jay Gould</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/sjgould/darwins_delay/</link><pubDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2024 23:28:27 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/sjgould/darwins_delay/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="darwins-delay"&gt;Darwin&amp;rsquo;s Delay&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few events inspire more speculation than long and unexplained pauses in the activities of
famous people. Rossini crowned a brilliant operatic career with William Tell and then wrote
almost nothing for the next thirty-five years. Dorothy Sayers abandoned Lord Peter Wimsey
at the height of his popularity and turned instead to God. Charles Darwin developed a radical
theory of evolution in 1838 and published it twenty-one years later only because A. R.
Wallace was about to scoop him.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Studies in European Realism by György Lukács</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/lukacs/studies_in_european_realism/</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2023 02:07:16 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/lukacs/studies_in_european_realism/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The articles contained in this book were written some ten years ago. Author and reader
may well ask why they should be republished just now. At first sight they might seem to
lack all topicality. Subject and tone alike may appear remote to a considerable section of
public opinion. I believe, however, that they have some topicality in that, without
entering upon any detailed polemics, they represent a point of view in opposition to
certain literary and philosophical trends still very much to the fore today.
Let us begin with the general atmosphere: the clouds of mysticism which once
surrounded the phenomena of literature with a poetic colour and warmth and created
an intimate and ‘‘interesting’’ atmosphere around them, have been dispersed. Things
now face us in a clear, sharp light which to many may seem cold and hard; a light shed
on them by the teachings of Marx. Marxism searches for the material roots of each
phenomenon, regards them in their historical connections and movement, ascertains the
laws of such movement and demonstrates their development from root to flower, and in
so doing lifts every phenomenon out of a merely emotional, irrational, mystic fog and
brings it to the bright light of understanding.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Marx, Race and Neoliberalism by Adolph Reed Jr.</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/adolph-reed-jr/marx_race_neoliberalism/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 Sep 2023 02:47:39 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/adolph-reed-jr/marx_race_neoliberalism/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A Marxist perspective can be most helpful for understanding race and racism
insofar as it per- ceives capitalism dialectically, as a social total- ity that
includes modes of production, relations of production, and the pragmatically
evolving ensemble of institutions and ideologies that lubricate and propel its
reproduction. From this perspective, Marxism’s most important contri- bution to
making sense of race and racism in the United States may be demystification. A
histori- cal materialist perspective should stress that “race”—which includes
“racism,” as one is unthinkable without the other—is a historically specific
ideology that emerged, took shape, and has evolved as a constitutive element
within a definite set of social relations anchored to a par- ticular system of
production.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Revolutionary Medicine by Ernesto Che Guevara</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/revolutionarey_medicine_che/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Aug 2023 07:31:37 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/revolutionarey_medicine_che/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Adapted from &lt;a href="https://www.marxists.org/archive/guevara/1960/08/19.htm"&gt;https://www.marxists.org/archive/guevara/1960/08/19.htm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was put onto this article from the reading of the terrific
text on the Cuban and Venezuelan healthcare systems and practices by Steven
Brouwer: &lt;a href="https://monthlyreview.org/product/revolutionary_doctors/"&gt;&amp;ldquo;Revolutionary Doctors: How Venezuela and Cuba Are Changing the World’s
Conception of Health Care&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This simple celebration, another among the hundreds of public functions with
which the Cuban people daily celebrate their liberty, the progress of all their
revolutionary laws, and their advances along the road to complete independence,
is of special interest to me.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Cuacasians Only: an excerpt from Robert Fogelson</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/suburbia/cuacasians_only/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Jul 2023 07:18:50 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/suburbia/cuacasians_only/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A small but very important subsection from Robert Fogelson&amp;rsquo;s book &amp;ldquo;Bourgeois
Nightmares: Suburbia, 1870-1930&amp;rdquo;. I would say it speaks for itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many subdividers also employed restrictions to exclude
‘‘undesirable’’ people as well as &amp;ldquo;undesirable&amp;rdquo; activities. By far the
most common of these provisions were racial covenants. Under
a typical covenant, an owner was forbidden to sell or lease the
property to a member of any of a number of allegedly undesirable
racial, ethnic, or religious groups. He or she was also forbidden
to allow a member of these groups, other than chauffeurs, gardeners, or domestic servants, to use or occupy the property. A few
subdividers had employed racial covenants in the mid-nineteenth
century. In Brookline, for example, one forbade &amp;ldquo;any negro or
native of Ireland&amp;rdquo; to occupy a dwelling, and in Baltimore another
barred the sale or lease of a house to &amp;ldquo;a negro or person of African
or Mongolian [that is, Asian] descent.&amp;rdquo; But such restrictions were
very much the exception before the 1890s. Indeed, not even the
most racist subdividers imposed racial covenants. A case in point
was Francis G. Newlands, the mining magnate and U.S. senator
who laid out Chevy Chase in the early 1890s. Newlands saw the
United States as &amp;ldquo;the home of the white race.&amp;rdquo; To him, &amp;ldquo;race tolerance&amp;rdquo; meant &amp;ldquo;race amalgamation,&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;race intolerance&amp;rdquo; meant
&amp;ldquo;race war.&amp;rdquo; Fusing the racism of the South with the racism of the
West, he called for repealing the Fifteenth Amendment, thereby
denying African-Americans, &amp;ldquo;an inferior race,&amp;rdquo; the right to vote,
and restricting immigration to &amp;ldquo;the white race,&amp;rdquo; thereby excluding Chinese, Japanese, and other Asians. Despite his outspoken racism, Newlands did not include racial covenants among the
minimum cost requirements and other restrictions he imposed
on the first subdivisions at Chevy Chase.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Conclusion to the Gift by Marcel Mauss</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/marcel-mauss/conclusion-to-the-gift/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jun 2023 05:03:51 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/marcel-mauss/conclusion-to-the-gift/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The conclusion to Mauss&amp;rsquo;s incredible essay on the uses and concepts of gifts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="moral-conclusions"&gt;Moral Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is possible to extend these observations to our own
societies. A considerable part of our morality and our lives
themselves are still permeated with this same atmosphere of
the gift, where obligation and liberty intermingle. Fortunately,
everything is still not wholly categorized in terms of buying
and selling. Things still have sentimental as well as venal value,
assuming values merely of this kind exist. We possess more
than a tradesman morality. There still remain people and
classes that keep to the morality of former times, and we
almost all observe it, at least at certain times of the year or
on certain occasions.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Socialism or Moralism by Bayard Rustin</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/socialism-or-moralism_rustin/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 03:30:51 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/socialism-or-moralism_rustin/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Cross posted from &lt;a href="https://nonsite.org/socialism-or-moralism/"&gt;Nonsite.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Passages between brackets are drawn from the manuscript version of the essay and differ slightly from the published variant.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Published July 7, 1970&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We on the democratic left are living through a real crisis. And precisely
because I believe the Socialist Party has a very vital role to play in this
period, I would like to say something about the problems we confront.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One aspect is that many people on the [so-called democratic] left today
substitute psychology for politics. Now, I have no objection to a lifestyle, or
how you wear your hair, or whether you eat pig’s feet[, or whether you want to
dress so one cannot distinguish between male and female except upon very close
inspection]. But to substitute this “how I feel, what my thing is,” for
politics, is an extremely dangerous attitude which the Socialist movement must
fight. In fact, the Socialist movement is one of the few movements which has the
credentials for fighting it.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Introduction: Restoration in Russia by Boris Kagarlitsky</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/restoration-in-russia/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 May 2023 02:35:24 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/restoration-in-russia/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This brief writing belongs to the Introduction to Boris Kagarlitsky&amp;rsquo;s book
&amp;ldquo;Restoration in Russia: Why Capitalism Failed&amp;rdquo;. The work is both a valuable
reflection of, and look into, the tumultuous years following the dissolution of
the USSR.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;You can&amp;rsquo;t hammer in a bolt.&amp;rsquo; This was among the slogans used by the
pro-government political bloc Russia&amp;rsquo;s Choice in its campaign for the
parliamentary elections of December 1993. Spokespeople for the bloc explained
to voters: it&amp;rsquo;s pointless to dream of a just society, so you have to reconcile
yourself to the new order. The slogan turned out to be unintentionally ironic.
The attempts by Yelstin, Gaidar and the other Russian &amp;lsquo;reformers&amp;rsquo; to construct
liberal capitalism in a country where there is neither a normal bourgeoise, nor
a market infrastructure, were a case of &amp;lsquo;hammering a bolt&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Global Neoliberal Practice: Institutions and Regulation in Africa by Graham Harrison</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/neoliberal-africa-global-practice/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2023 22:51:40 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/neoliberal-africa-global-practice/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This is a chapter out of Graham Harrison&amp;rsquo;s Book &amp;ldquo;Neoliberal Africa: The Impact
of Global Social Engineering&amp;rdquo;. Although the book is more of an essay containing
fragmentary thoughts, I found this chapter substantial in the sense that it
clearly outlined the various institutional avenues in which projects such as
neoliberalism cement their ideology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This chapter considers the global emergence of neoliberalism. It looks at the
ways in which neoliberal practice has emerged, expanded and established for
itself ‘paradigmatic’ status. In other words, it shows how neoliberalism has
shifted from an ambitious and embryonic set of policy interventions to
something resembling a framework or set of premisses within which policy is
articulated. The practices of neoliberalism have been iterated over such time
as to shift the habits, conduct and repertoire of development practice tout
court. The layering of large numbers of neoliberal policies has not only led to
a progressively more totalising implementation of liberalisation; it has also
defined the terms upon which policy and development are thought about and
articulated per se. This is, of course, not a completed process (in the last
chapter we developed a framework which is anathema to the idea of completed
processes, preferring instead a series of practices in place of means–ends
distinctions), but it has enabled neoliberal ideas to aspire to
‘meta-development’ status: that is, as the terms upon which development is
discussed rather than solely as a predominant model of development. At the
level of ideas, this shift or tendency is rather like the analysis of Hay in
which neoliberalism moves from normalising to normative (Hay 2004).&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Race into Culture: A Critical Genealogy of Cultural Identity by Walter Benn Michaels</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/walter-benn-michaels/geneology-race-into-culture/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Mar 2023 10:59:16 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/walter-benn-michaels/geneology-race-into-culture/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Due to the prolific number of footnotes that Michael&amp;rsquo;s article contains, the
essay will simply be linked to here. It is an important walk through the
trajectories that various essentialist concepts have taken in the course of modern
Northern American history. What surprised me most was this quasi-progess &amp;mdash; where
it appears that the concept of race has been disposed of, it&amp;rsquo;s kernel is
carried over into a different, yet sadly, familial form.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Soviet Literature by Maxim Gorky</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/maxim-gorky/soviet-literature/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 08:06:39 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/maxim-gorky/soviet-literature/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Herein is a speech delivered in August 1934, and published in 1935. It reappeared
in Gorky, Radek, Bukharin, Zhdanov and others “Soviet Writers’ Congress 1934,”
page 25-69, Lawrence &amp;amp; Wishart, 1977, and was transcribed by Jose Braz for the
Marxists Internet Archive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The role of the labour processes, which have converted a two-Legged animal into
man and created the basic elements of culture, has never been investigated as
deeply and thoroughly as it deserves. This is quite natural, for such research
would not be in the interests of the exploiters of labour. The latter, who use
the energy of the masses as a sort of raw material to be turned into money,
could not, of course, enhance the value of this raw material. Ever since remote
antiquity, when mankind was divided into slaves and slave-owners, they have
used the vital power of the toiling mass in the same way as we today use the
mechanical force of river currents. Primitive man has been depicted by the
historians of culture as a philosophizing idealist and mystic, a creator of
gods, a seeker after &lt;em&gt;“the meaning of life.”&lt;/em&gt; Primitive man has been saddled with
the mentality of a Jacob Böhme, a cobbler who lived at the end of the sixteenth
and the beginning of the seventeenth century and who occupied himself between
whiles with philosophy of a kind extremely popular among bourgeois mystics;
Böhme preached that &lt;em&gt;“Man should meditate on the Skies, on the Stars and the
Elements, and on the Creatures which do proceed from them, and likewise on the
Holy Angels, the Devil, Heaven and Hell.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Crisis of Bourgeois Philosophy by György Lukács</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/lukacs/crisis-of-bourgeois-philosophy/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Mar 2023 01:59:10 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/lukacs/crisis-of-bourgeois-philosophy/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Written in 1948.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact of the crisis has been stated not only by us Marxists. The concept of
“crisis” has long taken root in bourgeois philosophy. When, for example,
Siegfried Marck, a famous neo-Hegelian, wanted to define Rickert’s place in the
development of philosophy, he called him a thinker of the “pre-crisis era.”
Indeed, if we carefully trace the development of bourgeois philosophy in recent
decades, we will see that literally every two years the foundations of
philosophy are again and again called into question. It is no coincidence that
this development was initiated by Nietzsche’s program: a reassessment of all
values. This continues endlessly in modern philosophy; a year during which a
crisis did not break out in some area of philosophy is a year without any
events.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Introduction to Class Notes by Adolph Reed Jr.</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/adolph-reed-jr/intro-to-class-notes/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2023 02:15:15 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/adolph-reed-jr/intro-to-class-notes/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The text here is an extract from Adolph Reed Jr&amp;rsquo;s 2000 work &amp;ldquo;Class Notes&amp;rdquo;. This publication is the founding inspiration for the theme and title of this site here &amp;ndash; long live Reed.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book is built on commentary about current issues and events in american
politics over most of the 1990s. as such, it expresses an on-going attempt to
make sense of contemporary american political life from a critical perspective.
most of the essays published here appeared originally in substantially the same
form in my regular columns in the progressive and the village voice, or in
similar venues. writing in those venues presents a special challenge— to convey
complex, perhaps unconventional ideas clearly and concisely to a general
audience. i’ve found this challenge very useful partly because i work out my
own views on many issues by writing about them; to that extent, these essays
are much less a set of didactic pronoucements than a sustained attempt to think
things through, and the obligation to communicate those views effectively to
others encourages preciseness and clarity. having to ask constantly, “what
would this formulation mean to someone outside my own head or outside a
narrowly specialized community of discourse?” imposes a requirement to bring
abstractions down to the ground, to imagine how— if at all— they appear in,
explain or bear upon the daily world we inhabit and reproduce. the challenge
is more important, though, as a corrective to the flight from concreteness that
has increasingly beset left theorizing and social criticism, and as a result
political practice, in the u.s. in recent decades.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Posts Archive</title><link>https://classletters.org/archives/posts/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/archives/posts/</guid><description>This page contains an archive of all posts.</description></item></channel></rss>