<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>PMC on Class Letters</title><link>https://classletters.org/tags/pmc/</link><description>Recent content in PMC on Class Letters</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2023 02:15:15 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://classletters.org/tags/pmc/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Introduction to Class Notes by Adolph Reed Jr.</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/adolph-reed-jr/intro-to-class-notes/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2023 02:15:15 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/adolph-reed-jr/intro-to-class-notes/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The text here is an extract from Adolph Reed Jr&amp;rsquo;s 2000 work &amp;ldquo;Class Notes&amp;rdquo;. This publication is the founding inspiration for the theme and title of this site here &amp;ndash; long live Reed.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book is built on commentary about current issues and events in american
politics over most of the 1990s. as such, it expresses an on-going attempt to
make sense of contemporary american political life from a critical perspective.
most of the essays published here appeared originally in substantially the same
form in my regular columns in the progressive and the village voice, or in
similar venues. writing in those venues presents a special challenge— to convey
complex, perhaps unconventional ideas clearly and concisely to a general
audience. i’ve found this challenge very useful partly because i work out my
own views on many issues by writing about them; to that extent, these essays
are much less a set of didactic pronoucements than a sustained attempt to think
things through, and the obligation to communicate those views effectively to
others encourages preciseness and clarity. having to ask constantly, “what
would this formulation mean to someone outside my own head or outside a
narrowly specialized community of discourse?” imposes a requirement to bring
abstractions down to the ground, to imagine how— if at all— they appear in,
explain or bear upon the daily world we inhabit and reproduce. the challenge
is more important, though, as a corrective to the flight from concreteness that
has increasingly beset left theorizing and social criticism, and as a result
political practice, in the u.s. in recent decades.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>