<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Bourgeoise on Class Letters</title><link>https://classletters.org/tags/bourgeoise/</link><description>Recent content in Bourgeoise on Class Letters</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Jul 2023 07:18:50 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://classletters.org/tags/bourgeoise/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Cuacasians Only: an excerpt from Robert Fogelson</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/suburbia/cuacasians_only/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Jul 2023 07:18:50 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/suburbia/cuacasians_only/</guid><description>&lt;p>A small but very important subsection from Robert Fogelson&amp;rsquo;s book &amp;ldquo;Bourgeois
Nightmares: Suburbia, 1870-1930&amp;rdquo;. I would say it speaks for itself.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Many subdividers also employed restrictions to exclude
‘‘undesirable’’ people as well as &amp;ldquo;undesirable&amp;rdquo; activities. By far the
most common of these provisions were racial covenants. Under
a typical covenant, an owner was forbidden to sell or lease the
property to a member of any of a number of allegedly undesirable
racial, ethnic, or religious groups. He or she was also forbidden
to allow a member of these groups, other than chauffeurs, gardeners, or domestic servants, to use or occupy the property. A few
subdividers had employed racial covenants in the mid-nineteenth
century. In Brookline, for example, one forbade &amp;ldquo;any negro or
native of Ireland&amp;rdquo; to occupy a dwelling, and in Baltimore another
barred the sale or lease of a house to &amp;ldquo;a negro or person of African
or Mongolian [that is, Asian] descent.&amp;rdquo; But such restrictions were
very much the exception before the 1890s. Indeed, not even the
most racist subdividers imposed racial covenants. A case in point
was Francis G. Newlands, the mining magnate and U.S. senator
who laid out Chevy Chase in the early 1890s. Newlands saw the
United States as &amp;ldquo;the home of the white race.&amp;rdquo; To him, &amp;ldquo;race tolerance&amp;rdquo; meant &amp;ldquo;race amalgamation,&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;race intolerance&amp;rdquo; meant
&amp;ldquo;race war.&amp;rdquo; Fusing the racism of the South with the racism of the
West, he called for repealing the Fifteenth Amendment, thereby
denying African-Americans, &amp;ldquo;an inferior race,&amp;rdquo; the right to vote,
and restricting immigration to &amp;ldquo;the white race,&amp;rdquo; thereby excluding Chinese, Japanese, and other Asians. Despite his outspoken racism, Newlands did not include racial covenants among the
minimum cost requirements and other restrictions he imposed
on the first subdivisions at Chevy Chase.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Soviet Literature by Maxim Gorky</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/maxim-gorky/soviet-literature/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 08:06:39 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/maxim-gorky/soviet-literature/</guid><description>&lt;p>Herein is a speech delivered in August 1934, and published in 1935. It reappeared
in Gorky, Radek, Bukharin, Zhdanov and others “Soviet Writers’ Congress 1934,”
page 25-69, Lawrence &amp;amp; Wishart, 1977, and was transcribed by Jose Braz for the
Marxists Internet Archive.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>The role of the labour processes, which have converted a two-Legged animal into
man and created the basic elements of culture, has never been investigated as
deeply and thoroughly as it deserves. This is quite natural, for such research
would not be in the interests of the exploiters of labour. The latter, who use
the energy of the masses as a sort of raw material to be turned into money,
could not, of course, enhance the value of this raw material. Ever since remote
antiquity, when mankind was divided into slaves and slave-owners, they have
used the vital power of the toiling mass in the same way as we today use the
mechanical force of river currents. Primitive man has been depicted by the
historians of culture as a philosophizing idealist and mystic, a creator of
gods, a seeker after &lt;em>“the meaning of life.”&lt;/em> Primitive man has been saddled with
the mentality of a Jacob Böhme, a cobbler who lived at the end of the sixteenth
and the beginning of the seventeenth century and who occupied himself between
whiles with philosophy of a kind extremely popular among bourgeois mystics;
Böhme preached that &lt;em>“Man should meditate on the Skies, on the Stars and the
Elements, and on the Creatures which do proceed from them, and likewise on the
Holy Angels, the Devil, Heaven and Hell.&amp;quot;&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Crisis of Bourgeois Philosophy by György Lukács</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/lukacs/crisis-of-bourgeois-philosophy/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Mar 2023 01:59:10 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/lukacs/crisis-of-bourgeois-philosophy/</guid><description>&lt;p>Written in 1948.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The fact of the crisis has been stated not only by us Marxists. The concept of
“crisis” has long taken root in bourgeois philosophy. When, for example,
Siegfried Marck, a famous neo-Hegelian, wanted to define Rickert’s place in the
development of philosophy, he called him a thinker of the “pre-crisis era.”
Indeed, if we carefully trace the development of bourgeois philosophy in recent
decades, we will see that literally every two years the foundations of
philosophy are again and again called into question. It is no coincidence that
this development was initiated by Nietzsche’s program: a reassessment of all
values. This continues endlessly in modern philosophy; a year during which a
crisis did not break out in some area of philosophy is a year without any
events.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>