<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Irrationalism on Class Letters</title><link>https://classletters.org/tags/irrationalism/</link><description>Recent content in Irrationalism on Class Letters</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2025 01:51:19 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://classletters.org/tags/irrationalism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The 'Lethal Chamber' in Eugenic Thought: an excerpt from Breeding Superman: Nietzsche, Race and Eugenics in Edwardian and Interwar Britain by Dan Stone</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/nietzsche/breeding-superman-eugenics/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2025 01:51:19 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/nietzsche/breeding-superman-eugenics/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Chapter five from &lt;em&gt;Breeding Superman: Nietzsche, Race and Eugenics in Edwardian and Interwar Britain&lt;/em&gt; by Dan Stone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we have seen, before the First World War, and in some circles until well
into the interwar period, eugenics &amp;mdash; literally, ‘well born’ or ‘good stocks’&amp;mdash; was the height of sophisticated, ‘progressive’ thought.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Across Europe, the
novels and plays of the period, such as H. G. Wells’s &lt;em&gt;The New Machiavelli&lt;/em&gt;
(1911) and George Bernard Shaw’s &lt;em&gt;Man and Superman&lt;/em&gt; (1905), are suffused
with the language of race-regeneration and fears of physical deterioration. In
Arthur Schnitzler’s novel, &lt;em&gt;The Road to the Open&lt;/em&gt; (1908), Berthold Stauber, a
young and enthusiastic Viennese Jewish physician, tells his father, the
humane Dr Stauber, that ‘You need only consider, father, that the most
honest and consistent social hygiene would have the direct result of annihilating diseased people, or at any rate excluding them from all enjoyment of
life, and I don’t deny that I have all kinds of ideas tending in that way which
may seem cruel at the first glance.’ He went on to say that ‘You needn’t be
afraid, father, that I shall begin straight away to preach the murder of the
unhealthy and superfluous. But theoretically that’s certainly what my programme leads to.’&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Although primarily a conservative ideology, both left and
right were attracted to eugenic proposals. These ranged from ‘positive’ measures such as the encouragement of ‘hygienic marriage’, that is, marriage
between two people of good stock, to ‘negative’ measures such as sterilisation or segregation in order to ensure that the unfit, feeble-minded and
morally degenerate did not have children. In this chapter I will consider
eugenics in general, before concentrating on one aspect of its rhetoric which
to a post-Second World War audience is perhaps even more shocking than it
was to an Edwardian one.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Crisis of Bourgeois Philosophy by György Lukács</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/lukacs/crisis-of-bourgeois-philosophy/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Mar 2023 01:59:10 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/lukacs/crisis-of-bourgeois-philosophy/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Written in 1948.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact of the crisis has been stated not only by us Marxists. The concept of
“crisis” has long taken root in bourgeois philosophy. When, for example,
Siegfried Marck, a famous neo-Hegelian, wanted to define Rickert’s place in the
development of philosophy, he called him a thinker of the “pre-crisis era.”
Indeed, if we carefully trace the development of bourgeois philosophy in recent
decades, we will see that literally every two years the foundations of
philosophy are again and again called into question. It is no coincidence that
this development was initiated by Nietzsche’s program: a reassessment of all
values. This continues endlessly in modern philosophy; a year during which a
crisis did not break out in some area of philosophy is a year without any
events.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>