<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Literature on Class Letters</title><link>https://classletters.org/tags/literature/</link><description>Recent content in Literature on Class Letters</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2023 02:07:16 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://classletters.org/tags/literature/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Studies in European Realism by György Lukács</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/lukacs/studies_in_european_realism/</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2023 02:07:16 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/lukacs/studies_in_european_realism/</guid><description>&lt;p>The articles contained in this book were written some ten years ago. Author and reader
may well ask why they should be republished just now. At first sight they might seem to
lack all topicality. Subject and tone alike may appear remote to a considerable section of
public opinion. I believe, however, that they have some topicality in that, without
entering upon any detailed polemics, they represent a point of view in opposition to
certain literary and philosophical trends still very much to the fore today.
Let us begin with the general atmosphere: the clouds of mysticism which once
surrounded the phenomena of literature with a poetic colour and warmth and created
an intimate and ‘‘interesting’’ atmosphere around them, have been dispersed. Things
now face us in a clear, sharp light which to many may seem cold and hard; a light shed
on them by the teachings of Marx. Marxism searches for the material roots of each
phenomenon, regards them in their historical connections and movement, ascertains the
laws of such movement and demonstrates their development from root to flower, and in
so doing lifts every phenomenon out of a merely emotional, irrational, mystic fog and
brings it to the bright light of understanding.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Race into Culture: A Critical Genealogy of Cultural Identity by Walter Benn Michaels</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/walter-benn-michaels/geneology-race-into-culture/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Mar 2023 10:59:16 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/walter-benn-michaels/geneology-race-into-culture/</guid><description>&lt;p>Due to the prolific number of footnotes that Michael&amp;rsquo;s article contains, the
essay will simply be linked to here. It is an important walk through the
trajectories that various essentialist concepts have taken in the course of modern
Northern American history. What surprised me most was this quasi-progess &amp;mdash; where
it appears that the concept of race has been disposed of, it&amp;rsquo;s kernel is
carried over into a different, yet sadly, familial form.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Soviet Literature by Maxim Gorky</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/maxim-gorky/soviet-literature/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 08:06:39 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/maxim-gorky/soviet-literature/</guid><description>&lt;p>Herein is a speech delivered in August 1934, and published in 1935. It reappeared
in Gorky, Radek, Bukharin, Zhdanov and others “Soviet Writers’ Congress 1934,”
page 25-69, Lawrence &amp;amp; Wishart, 1977, and was transcribed by Jose Braz for the
Marxists Internet Archive.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>The role of the labour processes, which have converted a two-Legged animal into
man and created the basic elements of culture, has never been investigated as
deeply and thoroughly as it deserves. This is quite natural, for such research
would not be in the interests of the exploiters of labour. The latter, who use
the energy of the masses as a sort of raw material to be turned into money,
could not, of course, enhance the value of this raw material. Ever since remote
antiquity, when mankind was divided into slaves and slave-owners, they have
used the vital power of the toiling mass in the same way as we today use the
mechanical force of river currents. Primitive man has been depicted by the
historians of culture as a philosophizing idealist and mystic, a creator of
gods, a seeker after &lt;em>“the meaning of life.”&lt;/em> Primitive man has been saddled with
the mentality of a Jacob Böhme, a cobbler who lived at the end of the sixteenth
and the beginning of the seventeenth century and who occupied himself between
whiles with philosophy of a kind extremely popular among bourgeois mystics;
Böhme preached that &lt;em>“Man should meditate on the Skies, on the Stars and the
Elements, and on the Creatures which do proceed from them, and likewise on the
Holy Angels, the Devil, Heaven and Hell.&amp;quot;&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>