<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>IMF on Class Letters</title><link>https://classletters.org/tags/imf/</link><description>Recent content in IMF on Class Letters</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 May 2025 06:20:02 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://classletters.org/tags/imf/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Chile, an Investigation of Aid as Imperialism by Teresa Hayter</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/aid_as_imperialism_chile/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 May 2025 06:20:02 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/aid_as_imperialism_chile/</guid><description>&lt;p>Teresa Hayter wrote a book outlining her time and experience as a member of the , one of the - one sense an objective account&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>Structuralist Ideas on economics as usually propounded
purport to provide an alternative to orthodox or monetarist
ideas without drastically changing the constitutional
framework. They offer proposals for a programme of
expansion and redistribution of income, involving gradual
changes in the structure of the economy, to provide the
possibility of durable and stable growth. They oppose
deflationary policies of the IMF variety on the grounds
that they hurt the poorer sections of the population and
that they inhibit growth and the restructuring of the
economy. It is arguable that the Fret government was
trying to apply these ideas in its first two or three years in
office (1964-7). It appeared that it might have found a
middle way in economics, as in politics, between stagnation
and revolution. Its economic policies had some unorthodox
features which at first seemed to be rather successful. The
fact that their success was short-lived may possibly prove
that the international agencies are, in one sense, right, there
is no painless way of solving Chile&amp;rsquo;s economic problems,
without somebody&amp;rsquo;s interests being hurt. The question, of
course, is whose interests are hurt.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Global Neoliberal Practice: Institutions and Regulation in Africa by Graham Harrison</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/neoliberal-africa-global-practice/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2023 22:51:40 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/neoliberal-africa-global-practice/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is a chapter out of Graham Harrison&amp;rsquo;s Book &amp;ldquo;Neoliberal Africa: The Impact
of Global Social Engineering&amp;rdquo;. Although the book is more of an essay containing
fragmentary thoughts, I found this chapter substantial in the sense that it
clearly outlined the various institutional avenues in which projects such as
neoliberalism cement their ideology.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>This chapter considers the global emergence of neoliberalism. It looks at the
ways in which neoliberal practice has emerged, expanded and established for
itself ‘paradigmatic’ status. In other words, it shows how neoliberalism has
shifted from an ambitious and embryonic set of policy interventions to
something resembling a framework or set of premisses within which policy is
articulated. The practices of neoliberalism have been iterated over such time
as to shift the habits, conduct and repertoire of development practice tout
court. The layering of large numbers of neoliberal policies has not only led to
a progressively more totalising implementation of liberalisation; it has also
defined the terms upon which policy and development are thought about and
articulated per se. This is, of course, not a completed process (in the last
chapter we developed a framework which is anathema to the idea of completed
processes, preferring instead a series of practices in place of means–ends
distinctions), but it has enabled neoliberal ideas to aspire to
‘meta-development’ status: that is, as the terms upon which development is
discussed rather than solely as a predominant model of development. At the
level of ideas, this shift or tendency is rather like the analysis of Hay in
which neoliberalism moves from normalising to normative (Hay 2004).&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>