<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>medicine on Class Letters</title>
    <link>https://classletters.org/tags/medicine/</link>
    <description>Recent content in medicine on Class Letters</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 23:41:44 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://classletters.org/tags/medicine/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Cancer Prevention and Screening by Jason Fung; The Cancer Code</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/public_health/cancer_code/cancer_code_pt2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 23:41:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/public_health/cancer_code/cancer_code_pt2/</guid>
      <description>This is part 2 of the post on Jason Fung&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;Cancer Code&amp;rsquo;. I found this a remarkable case point in the iatrogenic potential of public health interventions in which the effect on mortality is masked by an early surrogate of survival; early detection. One tracked for long enough time, early detection does more harm than good, and thus, fails as a successful surrogate. You can find part one here.
I encourage everyone to read the entirety of Jason&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;The Cancer Code&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A False Dawn by Jason Fung; The Cancer Code</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/public_health/cancer_code/cancer_code/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Feb 2024 23:41:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/public_health/cancer_code/cancer_code/</guid>
      <description>This post will be in two parts, both of which I find are illustrative of the difficulties of public health strategies. One makes particularly obvious the severe misanthropic consequences of profit seeking drives in the areas of health and medicine, and the second is a remarkable case point in the iatrogenic potential of public health interventions which may be completely benevolent in intention &amp;ndash; something that all states irrespective of political structure must address.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revolutionary Medicine by Ernesto Che Guevara</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/revolutionarey_medicine_che/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Aug 2023 07:31:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/revolutionarey_medicine_che/</guid>
      <description>Adapted from https://www.marxists.org/archive/guevara/1960/08/19.htm
I was put onto this article from the reading of the terrific text on the Cuban and Venezuelan healthcare systems and practices by Steven Brouwer: &amp;ldquo;Revolutionary Doctors: How Venezuela and Cuba Are Changing the World’s Conception of Health Care&amp;rdquo;
This simple celebration, another among the hundreds of public functions with which the Cuban people daily celebrate their liberty, the progress of all their revolutionary laws, and their advances along the road to complete independence, is of special interest to me.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
