<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Chile on Class Letters</title><link>https://classletters.org/tags/chile/</link><description>Recent content in Chile on Class Letters</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 May 2025 06:20:02 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://classletters.org/tags/chile/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Chile, an Investigation of Aid as Imperialism by Teresa Hayter</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/aid_as_imperialism_chile/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 May 2025 06:20:02 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/aid_as_imperialism_chile/</guid><description>&lt;p>Teresa Hayter&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;Aid as Imperialism&amp;rsquo;, was one of the first somewhat critical
texts written about the post world-war II monetary institutions, from a so
called insider&amp;rsquo;s view. Having spent some time employed at the Overseas
Development Institute, the World Bank financed Teresa&amp;rsquo;s research on the
effectiveness of aid packages provided to Third World countries. Given it was
intended as a publication on behalf of the ODI, one certainly encounters a
report which offers an objective overview of the various policy approaches that
these institutions taken. The first half of the text, is an outline, not a
critique. The second half turns to evaluating the implementation of these
approaches in several countries. Here is where we find a critical evaluation,
which best portrays the inflexibility of foreign aid packages, which, Teresa
believed, were given more so as blanket prescriptions, dogmas even. A standard
buffet of currency devaluations and austerity measures &amp;mdash; liberalize,
liberalize, liberalize! It is for this reason that the Overseas Development
Institute rejected the original report for publication. Fortunately, it
eventually made it&amp;rsquo;s way to us common readers. The following is an excerpt from the
text, focusing on the involvement of these aid agencies in Chile, a country which is emblematic of the deep difficulties of modernization and sovereignty in the global periphery.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>