<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Class Letters</title>
    <link>https://classletters.org/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Class Letters</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 08:06:39 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://classletters.org/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Soviet Literature by Maxim Gorky</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/maxim-gorky/soviet-literature/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 08:06:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/maxim-gorky/soviet-literature/</guid>
      <description>THE ROLE of the labour processes, which have converted a two-Legged animal into man and created the basic elements of culture, has never been investigated as deeply and thoroughly as it deserves. This is quite natural, for such research would not be in the interests of the exploiters of labour. The latter, who use the energy of the masses as a sort of raw material to be turned into money, could not, of course, enhance the value of this raw material.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Crisis of Bourgeois Philosophy by György Lukács</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/lukacs/crisis-of-bourgeois-philosophy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Mar 2023 01:59:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/lukacs/crisis-of-bourgeois-philosophy/</guid>
      <description>Written in 1948.
The fact of the crisis has been stated not only by us Marxists. The concept of “crisis” has long taken root in bourgeois philosophy. When, for example, Siegfried Marck, a famous neo-Hegelian, wanted to define Rickert’s place in the development of philosophy, he called him a thinker of the “pre-crisis era.” Indeed, if we carefully trace the development of bourgeois philosophy in recent decades, we will see that literally every two years the foundations of philosophy are again and again called into question.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Class Notes by Adolph Reed Jr.</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/adolph-reed-jr/intro-to-class-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2023 02:15:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/adolph-reed-jr/intro-to-class-notes/</guid>
      <description>The text here is an extract from Adolph Reed Jr&amp;rsquo;s 2000 work &amp;ldquo;Class Notes&amp;rdquo;. This publication is the founding inspiration for the theme and title of this site here &amp;ndash; long live Reed.
This book is built on commentary about current issues and events in american politics over most of the 1990s. as such, it expresses an on-going attempt to make sense of contemporary american political life from a critical perspective.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
