<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Class Letters</title>
    <link>https://classletters.org/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Class Letters</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2023 22:51:40 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://classletters.org/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Global Neoliberal Practice: Institutions and Regulation in Africa by Graham Harrison</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/neoliberal-africa-global-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2023 22:51:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/neoliberal-africa-global-practice/</guid>
      <description>This is a chapter out of Graham Harrison&amp;rsquo;s Book &amp;ldquo;Neoliberal Africa: The Impact of Global Social Engineering&amp;rdquo;. Although the book is more of an essay containing fragmentary thoughts, I found this chapter substantial in the sense that it clearly outlined the various institutional avenues in which projects such as neoliberalism cement their ideology.
This chapter considers the global emergence of neoliberalism. It looks at the ways in which neoliberal practice has emerged, expanded and established for itself ‘paradigmatic’ status.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Race into Culture: A Critical Genealogy of Cultural Identity by Walter Benn Michaels </title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/walter-benn-michaels/geneology-race-into-culture/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Mar 2023 10:59:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/walter-benn-michaels/geneology-race-into-culture/</guid>
      <description>Anti-Imperial Americanism Thomas Nelson Page&amp;rsquo;s Red Rock was published in 1898, the year in which the United States annexed Hawaii, went to war in Cuba, seized the Philippines from Spain, and emerged as an imperial power. Needless to say, Red Rock, written the year before these events took place and written about events that had themselves taken place some thirty years earlier, is unconcerned with Cuba or the Philippines. But it is not unconcerned with American imperialism; indeed, American imperialism and, above all, the resistance to it, is its main subject.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Soviet Literature by Maxim Gorky</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/maxim-gorky/soviet-literature/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 08:06:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/maxim-gorky/soviet-literature/</guid>
      <description>Herein is a speech delivered in August 1934, and published in 1935. It reappeared in Gorky, Radek, Bukharin, Zhdanov and others “Soviet Writers’ Congress 1934,” page 25-69, Lawrence &amp;amp; Wishart, 1977, and was transcribed by Jose Braz for the Marxists Internet Archive.
The role of the labour processes, which have converted a two-Legged animal into man and created the basic elements of culture, has never been investigated as deeply and thoroughly as it deserves.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Crisis of Bourgeois Philosophy by György Lukács</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/lukacs/crisis-of-bourgeois-philosophy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Mar 2023 01:59:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/lukacs/crisis-of-bourgeois-philosophy/</guid>
      <description>Written in 1948.
The fact of the crisis has been stated not only by us Marxists. The concept of “crisis” has long taken root in bourgeois philosophy. When, for example, Siegfried Marck, a famous neo-Hegelian, wanted to define Rickert’s place in the development of philosophy, he called him a thinker of the “pre-crisis era.” Indeed, if we carefully trace the development of bourgeois philosophy in recent decades, we will see that literally every two years the foundations of philosophy are again and again called into question.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Class Notes by Adolph Reed Jr.</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/adolph-reed-jr/intro-to-class-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2023 02:15:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/adolph-reed-jr/intro-to-class-notes/</guid>
      <description>The text here is an extract from Adolph Reed Jr&amp;rsquo;s 2000 work &amp;ldquo;Class Notes&amp;rdquo;. This publication is the founding inspiration for the theme and title of this site here &amp;ndash; long live Reed.
This book is built on commentary about current issues and events in american politics over most of the 1990s. as such, it expresses an on-going attempt to make sense of contemporary american political life from a critical perspective.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
