<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Class Letters</title>
    <link>https://classletters.org/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Class Letters</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 Sep 2024 01:58:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://classletters.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>An Image of Africa: Racism in Conrad&#39;s Heart of Darkness by Chinua Achebe</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/achebe_conrad_hod/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Sep 2024 01:58:15 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/achebe_conrad_hod/</guid>
      <description>In The Fall of 1974 I was walking one day from the English Depart- ment at the University of Massachusetts to a parking lot. It was a fine autumn morning such as encouraged friendliness to passing strangers. Brisk youngsters were hurrying in all directions, many of them obviously freshmen in their first flush of enthusiasm.An older man going the same way as I turned and remarked to me how very young they came these days.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seven Types of Obloquy: Traversties of Marxism by Norman Geras:</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/geras/seven_types/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jun 2024 04:01:32 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/geras/seven_types/</guid>
      <description>I see this as a terrific example of where reasoned and well formed criticism can stand on its own, in spite of the divergent trajectory which the author appears to take later on in his life through his reactionary offshoots.&#xA;As with any analytical field of inquiry which aspires to achieving insights, syntheses and increased understandings of the world, Marxism contains a broad array of unique and differeing perspectives, some of which fall far short of the high standard of rigor demanded of a scientific field.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About Class Letters</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2024 23:03:17 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/about/</guid>
      <description>Class Letters seeks to be a regularly updated feed of articles, unified by the goal of building a socialist~communist consciousness, itself thereafter seeking a real body politic.&#xA;Alongside more clearly defined political and philosophical texts, Class Letters incorporates works from different scientific, and health fields, bound by the commitment that communist work can, and should be scientific. Without a doubt, there is a purposeful goal of educating, and the goals of the autodidact are encouraged &amp;ndash; we have a reverence for education and it&amp;rsquo;s transformative potentials.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capital Account Liberalization and the Developing Nations, an excerpt from José Antonio Ocampo</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/capital_account_liberalization/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2024 22:34:24 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/capital_account_liberalization/</guid>
      <description>In looking to imagine and crystallise potential alternatives to the seemingly unending vortex of underdevelopment and poverty in third and second world nations, an understanding of the deficiencies and insufficiencies of the current macroeconomic arrangement is an obvious starting point. The post-Bretton Woods monetary consensus, which promised to guarantee mutual &amp;lsquo;real growth&amp;rsquo; through endless liberalization of domestic markets and fluctuating exchange rates, has in whole been failure for developing countries. Instead, of self-sufficiency and self-confidence, there isn&amp;rsquo;t even what one one called &amp;lsquo;multi-lateral beneficence&amp;rsquo;, but rather, a reliance and dependency on the most powerful players in the game, at the mercy of commodities swings and speculative exuberance (rather than being &amp;rsquo;liberated&amp;rsquo; and domestically sound, buffered from &amp;lsquo;shocks&amp;rsquo;).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cancer Prevention and Screening by Jason Fung; The Cancer Code</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/public_health/cancer_code/cancer_code_pt2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 23:41:44 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/public_health/cancer_code/cancer_code_pt2/</guid>
      <description>This is part 2 of the post on Jason Fung&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;Cancer Code&amp;rsquo;. I found this a remarkable case point in the iatrogenic potential of public health interventions in which the effect on mortality is masked by a surrogate of survival; early detection. When tracked for long enough time, early detection does more harm than good, and thus, fails as a successful surrogate. You can find part one here.&#xA;I encourage everyone to read the entirety of Jason&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;The Cancer Code&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A False Dawn by Jason Fung; The Cancer Code</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/public_health/cancer_code/cancer_code/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Feb 2024 23:41:44 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/public_health/cancer_code/cancer_code/</guid>
      <description>This post will be in two parts, both of which I find are illustrative of the difficulties of public health strategies. One makes particularly obvious the severe misanthropic consequences of profit seeking drives in the areas of health and medicine, and the second is a remarkable case point in the iatrogenic potential of public health interventions which may be completely benevolent in intention &amp;ndash; something that all states irrespective of political structure must address.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why no Roman Industrial Revolution? by Bret Devereaux</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/why_no_roman_ind_rev/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Feb 2024 23:20:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/why_no_roman_ind_rev/</guid>
      <description>Original at https://acoup.blog/2022/08/26/collections-why-no-roman-industrial-revolution/ . Linked to it via Paul Cockshott.&#xA;The Question That said this is a question that is not absurd a priori. As we’ll see, the Roman Empire was never close to an industrial revolution – a great many of the preconditions were missing – but the idea that it might have been on the cusp of being something like a modern economy did once have its day in the scholarship.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Darwin&#39;s Delay by Stephen Jay Gould</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/sjgould/darwins_delay/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2024 23:28:27 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/sjgould/darwins_delay/</guid>
      <description>Darwin&amp;rsquo;s Delay Few events inspire more speculation than long and unexplained pauses in the activities of famous people. Rossini crowned a brilliant operatic career with William Tell and then wrote almost nothing for the next thirty-five years. Dorothy Sayers abandoned Lord Peter Wimsey at the height of his popularity and turned instead to God. Charles Darwin developed a radical theory of evolution in 1838 and published it twenty-one years later only because A.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Studies in European Realism by György Lukács</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/lukacs/studies_in_european_realism/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2023 02:07:16 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/lukacs/studies_in_european_realism/</guid>
      <description>The articles contained in this book were written some ten years ago. Author and reader may well ask why they should be republished just now. At first sight they might seem to lack all topicality. Subject and tone alike may appear remote to a considerable section of public opinion. I believe, however, that they have some topicality in that, without entering upon any detailed polemics, they represent a point of view in opposition to certain literary and philosophical trends still very much to the fore today.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Marx, Race and Neoliberalism by Adolph Reed Jr.</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/adolph-reed-jr/marx_race_neoliberalism/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Sep 2023 02:47:39 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/adolph-reed-jr/marx_race_neoliberalism/</guid>
      <description>A Marxist perspective can be most helpful for understanding race and racism insofar as it per- ceives capitalism dialectically, as a social total- ity that includes modes of production, relations of production, and the pragmatically evolving ensemble of institutions and ideologies that lubricate and propel its reproduction. From this perspective, Marxism’s most important contri- bution to making sense of race and racism in the United States may be demystification. A histori- cal materialist perspective should stress that “race”—which includes “racism,” as one is unthinkable without the other—is a historically specific ideology that emerged, took shape, and has evolved as a constitutive element within a definite set of social relations anchored to a par- ticular system of production.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revolutionary Medicine by Ernesto Che Guevara</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/revolutionarey_medicine_che/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Aug 2023 07:31:37 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/revolutionarey_medicine_che/</guid>
      <description>Adapted from https://www.marxists.org/archive/guevara/1960/08/19.htm&#xA;I was put onto this article from the reading of the terrific text on the Cuban and Venezuelan healthcare systems and practices by Steven Brouwer: &amp;ldquo;Revolutionary Doctors: How Venezuela and Cuba Are Changing the World’s Conception of Health Care&amp;rdquo;&#xA;This simple celebration, another among the hundreds of public functions with which the Cuban people daily celebrate their liberty, the progress of all their revolutionary laws, and their advances along the road to complete independence, is of special interest to me.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cuacasians Only: an excerpt from Robert Fogelson</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/suburbia/cuacasians_only/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jul 2023 07:18:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/suburbia/cuacasians_only/</guid>
      <description>A small but very important subsection from Robert Fogelson&amp;rsquo;s book &amp;ldquo;Bourgeois Nightmares: Suburbia, 1870-1930&amp;rdquo;. I would say it speaks for itself.&#xA;Many subdividers also employed restrictions to exclude ‘‘undesirable’’ people as well as &amp;ldquo;undesirable&amp;rdquo; activities. By far the most common of these provisions were racial covenants. Under a typical covenant, an owner was forbidden to sell or lease the property to a member of any of a number of allegedly undesirable racial, ethnic, or religious groups.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conclusion to the Gift by Marcel Mauss</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/marcel-mauss/conclusion-to-the-gift/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jun 2023 05:03:51 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/marcel-mauss/conclusion-to-the-gift/</guid>
      <description>The conclusion to Mauss&amp;rsquo;s incredible essay on the uses and concepts of gifts.&#xA;Moral Conclusions It is possible to extend these observations to our own societies. A considerable part of our morality and our lives themselves are still permeated with this same atmosphere of the gift, where obligation and liberty intermingle. Fortunately, everything is still not wholly categorized in terms of buying and selling. Things still have sentimental as well as venal value, assuming values merely of this kind exist.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Socialism or Moralism by Bayard Rustin</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/socialism-or-moralism_rustin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 03:30:51 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/socialism-or-moralism_rustin/</guid>
      <description>Cross posted from Nonsite.org.&#xA;Passages between brackets are drawn from the manuscript version of the essay and differ slightly from the published variant.&#xA;Published July 7, 1970&#xA;We on the democratic left are living through a real crisis. And precisely because I believe the Socialist Party has a very vital role to play in this period, I would like to say something about the problems we confront.&#xA;One aspect is that many people on the [so-called democratic] left today substitute psychology for politics.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introduction: Restoration in Russia by Boris Kagarlitsky</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/restoration-in-russia/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 May 2023 02:35:24 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/restoration-in-russia/</guid>
      <description>This brief writing belongs to the Introduction to Boris Kagarlitsky&amp;rsquo;s book &amp;ldquo;Restoration in Russia: Why Capitalism Failed&amp;rdquo;. The work is both a valuable reflection of, and look into, the tumultuous years following the dissolution of the USSR.&#xA;&amp;lsquo;You can&amp;rsquo;t hammer in a bolt.&amp;rsquo; This was among the slogans used by the pro-government political bloc Russia&amp;rsquo;s Choice in its campaign for the parliamentary elections of December 1993. Spokespeople for the bloc explained to voters: it&amp;rsquo;s pointless to dream of a just society, so you have to reconcile yourself to the new order.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global Neoliberal Practice: Institutions and Regulation in Africa by Graham Harrison</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/neoliberal-africa-global-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2023 22:51:40 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/neoliberal-africa-global-practice/</guid>
      <description>This is a chapter out of Graham Harrison&amp;rsquo;s Book &amp;ldquo;Neoliberal Africa: The Impact of Global Social Engineering&amp;rdquo;. Although the book is more of an essay containing fragmentary thoughts, I found this chapter substantial in the sense that it clearly outlined the various institutional avenues in which projects such as neoliberalism cement their ideology.&#xA;This chapter considers the global emergence of neoliberalism. It looks at the ways in which neoliberal practice has emerged, expanded and established for itself ‘paradigmatic’ status.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Race into Culture: A Critical Genealogy of Cultural Identity by Walter Benn Michaels </title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/walter-benn-michaels/geneology-race-into-culture/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Mar 2023 10:59:16 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/walter-benn-michaels/geneology-race-into-culture/</guid>
      <description>Due to the prolific number of footnotes that Michael&amp;rsquo;s article contains, the essay will simply be linked to here. It is an important walk through the trajectories that various essentialist concepts have taken in the course of modern Northern American history. What surprised me most was this quasi-progess &amp;mdash; where it appears that the concept of race has been disposed of, it&amp;rsquo;s kernel is carried over into a different, yet sadly, familial form.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Soviet Literature by Maxim Gorky</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/maxim-gorky/soviet-literature/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 08:06:39 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/maxim-gorky/soviet-literature/</guid>
      <description>Herein is a speech delivered in August 1934, and published in 1935. It reappeared in Gorky, Radek, Bukharin, Zhdanov and others “Soviet Writers’ Congress 1934,” page 25-69, Lawrence &amp;amp; Wishart, 1977, and was transcribed by Jose Braz for the Marxists Internet Archive.&#xA;The role of the labour processes, which have converted a two-Legged animal into man and created the basic elements of culture, has never been investigated as deeply and thoroughly as it deserves.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Crisis of Bourgeois Philosophy by György Lukács</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/lukacs/crisis-of-bourgeois-philosophy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Mar 2023 01:59:10 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/lukacs/crisis-of-bourgeois-philosophy/</guid>
      <description>Written in 1948.&#xA;The fact of the crisis has been stated not only by us Marxists. The concept of “crisis” has long taken root in bourgeois philosophy. When, for example, Siegfried Marck, a famous neo-Hegelian, wanted to define Rickert’s place in the development of philosophy, he called him a thinker of the “pre-crisis era.” Indeed, if we carefully trace the development of bourgeois philosophy in recent decades, we will see that literally every two years the foundations of philosophy are again and again called into question.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Class Notes by Adolph Reed Jr.</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/adolph-reed-jr/intro-to-class-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2023 02:15:15 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/adolph-reed-jr/intro-to-class-notes/</guid>
      <description>The text here is an extract from Adolph Reed Jr&amp;rsquo;s 2000 work &amp;ldquo;Class Notes&amp;rdquo;. This publication is the founding inspiration for the theme and title of this site here &amp;ndash; long live Reed.&#xA;This book is built on commentary about current issues and events in american politics over most of the 1990s. as such, it expresses an on-going attempt to make sense of contemporary american political life from a critical perspective.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
