<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Foreign Exchange on Class Letters</title>
    <link>https://classletters.org/tags/foreign-exchange/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Foreign Exchange on Class Letters</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 May 2025 06:20:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://classletters.org/tags/foreign-exchange/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Chile, an Investigation of Aid as Imperialism by Teresa Hayter</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/aid_as_imperialism_chile/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 May 2025 06:20:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/aid_as_imperialism_chile/</guid>
      <description>Teresa Hayter wrote a book outlining her time and experience as a member of the , one of the - one sense an objective account&#xA;Structuralist Ideas on economics as usually propounded purport to provide an alternative to orthodox or monetarist ideas without drastically changing the constitutional framework. They offer proposals for a programme of expansion and redistribution of income, involving gradual changes in the structure of the economy, to provide the possibility of durable and stable growth.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capital Account Liberalization and the Developing Nations, an excerpt from José Antonio Ocampo</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/capital_account_liberalization/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2024 22:34:24 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/capital_account_liberalization/</guid>
      <description>In looking to imagine and crystallise potential alternatives to the seemingly unending vortex of underdevelopment and poverty in third and second world nations, an understanding of the deficiencies and insufficiencies of the current macroeconomic arrangement is an obvious starting point. The post-Bretton Woods monetary consensus, which promised to guarantee mutual &amp;lsquo;real growth&amp;rsquo; through endless liberalization of domestic markets and fluctuating exchange rates, has in whole been failure for developing countries. Instead, of self-sufficiency and self-confidence, there isn&amp;rsquo;t even what one one called &amp;lsquo;multi-lateral beneficence&amp;rsquo;, but rather, a reliance and dependency on the most powerful players in the game, at the mercy of commodities swings and speculative exuberance (rather than being &amp;rsquo;liberated&amp;rsquo; and domestically sound, buffered from &amp;lsquo;shocks&amp;rsquo;).</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
