<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Political Theory on Class Letters</title><link>https://classletters.org/tags/political-theory/</link><description>Recent content in Political Theory on Class Letters</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 06:18:49 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://classletters.org/tags/political-theory/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Decision-Making in a good society: The case for nested councils by Stephen R. Shalom</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/decision_making_postcap/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 06:18:49 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/decision_making_postcap/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="decision-making-in-a-good-society-the-case-for-nested-councils-by-stephen-r-shalom">Decision-Making in a Good Society: The Case for Nested Councils by Stephen R. Shalom&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Stephen R. Shalom is emeritus professor of Political Science at William Paterson University of New Jersey, USA. He is a member of the editorial board
of New Politics, and a long-time activist in peace and justice movements.
Among other works, he is the author of &lt;em>Which Side Are You On? An Introduction
to Politics (Longman, 2003)&lt;/em>, &amp;ldquo;Parpolity: A Political System for a Good Society,&amp;rdquo;
in &lt;em>Real Utopia: Participatory Society for the 21st Century, ed. Chris Spannos, AK
Press, 2008)&lt;/em> and editor of &lt;em>Socialist Visions&lt;/em> (South End Press, 1983).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Conclusion to the Gift by Marcel Mauss</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/marcel-mauss/conclusion-to-the-gift/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jun 2023 05:03:51 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/marcel-mauss/conclusion-to-the-gift/</guid><description>&lt;p>The conclusion to Mauss&amp;rsquo;s incredible essay on the uses and concepts of gifts.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="moral-conclusions">Moral Conclusions&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>It is possible to extend these observations to our own
societies. A considerable part of our morality and our lives
themselves are still permeated with this same atmosphere of
the gift, where obligation and liberty intermingle. Fortunately,
everything is still not wholly categorized in terms of buying
and selling. Things still have sentimental as well as venal value,
assuming values merely of this kind exist. We possess more
than a tradesman morality. There still remain people and
classes that keep to the morality of former times, and we
almost all observe it, at least at certain times of the year or
on certain occasions.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>