<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Politics on Class Letters</title><link>https://classletters.org/tags/politics/</link><description>Recent content in Politics on Class Letters</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 03:30:51 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://classletters.org/tags/politics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Socialism or Moralism by Bayard Rustin</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/socialism-or-moralism_rustin/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 03:30:51 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/socialism-or-moralism_rustin/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Cross posted from &lt;a href="https://nonsite.org/socialism-or-moralism/"&gt;Nonsite.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Passages between brackets are drawn from the manuscript version of the essay and differ slightly from the published variant.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Published July 7, 1970&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We on the democratic left are living through a real crisis. And precisely
because I believe the Socialist Party has a very vital role to play in this
period, I would like to say something about the problems we confront.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One aspect is that many people on the [so-called democratic] left today
substitute psychology for politics. Now, I have no objection to a lifestyle, or
how you wear your hair, or whether you eat pig’s feet[, or whether you want to
dress so one cannot distinguish between male and female except upon very close
inspection]. But to substitute this “how I feel, what my thing is,” for
politics, is an extremely dangerous attitude which the Socialist movement must
fight. In fact, the Socialist movement is one of the few movements which has the
credentials for fighting it.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Introduction: Restoration in Russia by Boris Kagarlitsky</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/restoration-in-russia/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 May 2023 02:35:24 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/restoration-in-russia/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This brief writing belongs to the Introduction to Boris Kagarlitsky&amp;rsquo;s book
&amp;ldquo;Restoration in Russia: Why Capitalism Failed&amp;rdquo;. The work is both a valuable
reflection of, and look into, the tumultuous years following the dissolution of
the USSR.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;You can&amp;rsquo;t hammer in a bolt.&amp;rsquo; This was among the slogans used by the
pro-government political bloc Russia&amp;rsquo;s Choice in its campaign for the
parliamentary elections of December 1993. Spokespeople for the bloc explained
to voters: it&amp;rsquo;s pointless to dream of a just society, so you have to reconcile
yourself to the new order. The slogan turned out to be unintentionally ironic.
The attempts by Yelstin, Gaidar and the other Russian &amp;lsquo;reformers&amp;rsquo; to construct
liberal capitalism in a country where there is neither a normal bourgeoise, nor
a market infrastructure, were a case of &amp;lsquo;hammering a bolt&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>