<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Capitalism on Class Letters</title><link>https://classletters.org/tags/capitalism/</link><description>Recent content in Capitalism on Class Letters</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2025 21:52:32 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://classletters.org/tags/capitalism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Theory of the Innovative Organization by William Lazonick</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/lazonick/theory_of_innovative_organization/</link><pubDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2025 21:52:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/lazonick/theory_of_innovative_organization/</guid><description>&lt;p>An excerpt from William Lazonick&amp;rsquo;s terrific work &amp;ldquo;&lt;em>Business Organization and the
Myth of the Market Economy&lt;/em>&amp;rdquo;, a book that offers a critique of what a &amp;lsquo;market
economy&amp;rsquo; is purported to be, through an evaluation of the strategies and
economic histories of businesses within what can be called &amp;ldquo;actually existing
capitalism&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>Here, at the risk of a small amount of
repetition, I shall supplement that discussion by focusing on the nature
of fixed costs, the different sources of uncertainty the innovative organization faces, and the relation between organizational capability and technological change.
Through its investment activities, a business organization commits financial resources to specific processes to make particular products with
the expectation of reaping financial returns. Once they are committed,
the productive assets of the organization represent fixed costs that must
then be recouped by the production and sale of output. If, through the
sale of sufficient output, investments could generate expected financial
returns instantaneously, fixed costs would not represent an economic
problem to the organization. But then, we would probably not call the
“assets” underlying these costs “investments.” Indeed, we might not even
deem it appropriate to call these costs “fixed” or the entity that incurs
them a firm. The problem of fixed costs occurs because the production
and sale of the enterprise’s output occur neither instantaneously nor with
certainty. The basic economic problem that confronts the capitalist enterprise is to transform fixed costs into revenue-generating products to realize financial returns. An analysis of how and with what success the business organization manages this transformation is the key to understanding
technological change, value creation, and economic growth.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Decision-Making in a Good Society: The Case for Nested Councils by Stephen R. Shalom</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/decision_making/decision_making_postcap/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 06:18:49 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/decision_making/decision_making_postcap/</guid><description>&lt;p>Stephen R. Shalom is emeritus professor of Political Science at William Paterson University of New Jersey, USA. He is a member of the editorial board
of New Politics, and a long-time activist in peace and justice movements.
Among other works, he is the author of &lt;em>Which Side Are You On? An Introduction
to Politics (Longman, 2003)&lt;/em>, &amp;ldquo;Parpolity: A Political System for a Good Society,&amp;rdquo;
in &lt;em>Real Utopia: Participatory Society for the 21st Century, ed. Chris Spannos, AK
Press, 2008)&lt;/em> and editor of &lt;em>Socialist Visions&lt;/em> (South End Press, 1983).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Cancer Prevention and Screening by Jason Fung; The Cancer Code</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/public_health/cancer_code/cancer_code_pt2/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 23:41:44 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/public_health/cancer_code/cancer_code_pt2/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is part 2 of the post on Jason Fung&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;Cancer Code&amp;rsquo;. I found this a
remarkable case point in the iatrogenic potential of public health
interventions in which the effect on mortality is masked by a surrogate
of survival; early detection. When tracked for long enough time, early detection
does more harm than good, and thus, fails as a successful surrogate. You can
find part one
&lt;a href="https://classletters.org/posts/biology/public_health/cancer_code/">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I encourage everyone to read the entirety of Jason&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;The Cancer Code&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s a
terrific work of &amp;lsquo;popular&amp;rsquo; scientific writing, a story as much about
the biology of Cancer as it is about the sociology of biomedical practice and
research.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A False Dawn by Jason Fung; The Cancer Code</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/public_health/cancer_code/cancer_code/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Feb 2024 23:41:44 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/public_health/cancer_code/cancer_code/</guid><description>&lt;p>This post will be in two parts, both of which I find are illustrative of the
difficulties of public health strategies. One makes particularly obvious the
severe misanthropic consequences of profit seeking drives in the areas of
health and medicine, and the second is a remarkable case point in the
iatrogenic potential of public health interventions which may be completely
benevolent in intention &amp;ndash; something that all states irrespective of political
structure must address. Part one is contained below, you can find part two (here)[]&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>