<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>united-states on Class Letters</title>
    <link>https://classletters.org/tags/united-states/</link>
    <description>Recent content in united-states on Class Letters</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Jul 2023 07:18:50 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://classletters.org/tags/united-states/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Cuacasians Only: an excerpt from Robert Fogelson</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/suburbia/cuacasians_only/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jul 2023 07:18:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/suburbia/cuacasians_only/</guid>
      <description>A small but very important subsection from Robert Fogelson&amp;rsquo;s book &amp;ldquo;Bourgeois Nightmares: Suburbia, 1870-1930&amp;rdquo;. I would say it speaks for itself.
Many subdividers also employed restrictions to exclude ‘‘undesirable’’ people as well as &amp;ldquo;undesirable&amp;rdquo; activities. By far the most common of these provisions were racial covenants. Under a typical covenant, an owner was forbidden to sell or lease the property to a member of any of a number of allegedly undesirable racial, ethnic, or religious groups.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Socialism or Moralism by Bayard Rustin</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/socialism-or-moralism_rustin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 03:30:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/socialism-or-moralism_rustin/</guid>
      <description>Cross posted from Nonsite.org.
Passages between brackets are drawn from the manuscript version of the essay and differ slightly from the published variant.
Published July 7, 1970
We on the democratic left are living through a real crisis. And precisely because I believe the Socialist Party has a very vital role to play in this period, I would like to say something about the problems we confront.
One aspect is that many people on the [so-called democratic] left today substitute psychology for politics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Race into Culture: A Critical Genealogy of Cultural Identity by Walter Benn Michaels </title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/walter-benn-michaels/geneology-race-into-culture/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Mar 2023 10:59:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/walter-benn-michaels/geneology-race-into-culture/</guid>
      <description>Due to the prolific number of footnotes that Michael&amp;rsquo;s article contains, the essay will simply be linked to here. It is an important walk through the trajectories that various essentialist concepts have taken in the course of modern Northern American history. What surprised me most was this quasi-progess &amp;mdash; where it appears that the concept of race has been disposed of, it&amp;rsquo;s kernel is carried over into a different, yet sadly, familial form.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
