<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>IMF on Class Letters</title>
    <link>https://classletters.org/tags/imf/</link>
    <description>Recent content in IMF on Class Letters</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 May 2025 06:20:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://classletters.org/tags/imf/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Chile, an Investigation of Aid as Imperialism by Teresa Hayter</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/aid_as_imperialism_chile/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 May 2025 06:20:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/aid_as_imperialism_chile/</guid>
      <description>Teresa Hayter wrote a book outlining her time and experience as a member of the , one of the - one sense an objective account&#xA;Structuralist Ideas on economics as usually propounded purport to provide an alternative to orthodox or monetarist ideas without drastically changing the constitutional framework. They offer proposals for a programme of expansion and redistribution of income, involving gradual changes in the structure of the economy, to provide the possibility of durable and stable growth.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global Neoliberal Practice: Institutions and Regulation in Africa by Graham Harrison</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/neoliberal-africa-global-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2023 22:51:40 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/neoliberal-africa-global-practice/</guid>
      <description>This is a chapter out of Graham Harrison&amp;rsquo;s Book &amp;ldquo;Neoliberal Africa: The Impact of Global Social Engineering&amp;rdquo;. Although the book is more of an essay containing fragmentary thoughts, I found this chapter substantial in the sense that it clearly outlined the various institutional avenues in which projects such as neoliberalism cement their ideology.&#xA;This chapter considers the global emergence of neoliberalism. It looks at the ways in which neoliberal practice has emerged, expanded and established for itself ‘paradigmatic’ status.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
