<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Segregation on Class Letters</title><link>https://classletters.org/tags/segregation/</link><description>Recent content in Segregation on Class Letters</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Jul 2023 07:18:50 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://classletters.org/tags/segregation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Cuacasians Only: an excerpt from Robert Fogelson</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/suburbia/cuacasians_only/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Jul 2023 07:18:50 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/suburbia/cuacasians_only/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A small but very important subsection from Robert Fogelson&amp;rsquo;s book &amp;ldquo;Bourgeois
Nightmares: Suburbia, 1870-1930&amp;rdquo;. I would say it speaks for itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many subdividers also employed restrictions to exclude
‘‘undesirable’’ people as well as &amp;ldquo;undesirable&amp;rdquo; activities. By far the
most common of these provisions were racial covenants. Under
a typical covenant, an owner was forbidden to sell or lease the
property to a member of any of a number of allegedly undesirable
racial, ethnic, or religious groups. He or she was also forbidden
to allow a member of these groups, other than chauffeurs, gardeners, or domestic servants, to use or occupy the property. A few
subdividers had employed racial covenants in the mid-nineteenth
century. In Brookline, for example, one forbade &amp;ldquo;any negro or
native of Ireland&amp;rdquo; to occupy a dwelling, and in Baltimore another
barred the sale or lease of a house to &amp;ldquo;a negro or person of African
or Mongolian [that is, Asian] descent.&amp;rdquo; But such restrictions were
very much the exception before the 1890s. Indeed, not even the
most racist subdividers imposed racial covenants. A case in point
was Francis G. Newlands, the mining magnate and U.S. senator
who laid out Chevy Chase in the early 1890s. Newlands saw the
United States as &amp;ldquo;the home of the white race.&amp;rdquo; To him, &amp;ldquo;race tolerance&amp;rdquo; meant &amp;ldquo;race amalgamation,&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;race intolerance&amp;rdquo; meant
&amp;ldquo;race war.&amp;rdquo; Fusing the racism of the South with the racism of the
West, he called for repealing the Fifteenth Amendment, thereby
denying African-Americans, &amp;ldquo;an inferior race,&amp;rdquo; the right to vote,
and restricting immigration to &amp;ldquo;the white race,&amp;rdquo; thereby excluding Chinese, Japanese, and other Asians. Despite his outspoken racism, Newlands did not include racial covenants among the
minimum cost requirements and other restrictions he imposed
on the first subdivisions at Chevy Chase.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>