<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Marxism on Class Letters</title>
    <link>https://classletters.org/tags/marxism/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Marxism on Class Letters</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2024 04:17:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://classletters.org/tags/marxism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Weapon of Theory by Amilcar Cabral</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/cabral/weapon_of_theory/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2024 04:17:05 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/cabral/weapon_of_theory/</guid>
      <description>Published in 1966. The text speaks for itself &amp;ndash; a terrific contextualisation of the National Liberation Movements.&#xA;If any of us came to Cuba with doubts in our mind about the solidity, strength, maturity and vitality of the Cuban Revolution, these doubts have been removed by what we have been able to see. Our hearts are now warmed by an unshakeable certainty which gives us courage in the difficult but glorious struggle against the common enemy: no power in the world will be able to destroy this Cuban Revolution, which is creating in the countryside and in the towns not only a new life but also — and even more important — a New Man, fully conscious of his national, continental and international rights and duties.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seven Types of Obloquy: Traversties of Marxism by Norman Geras:</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/geras/seven_types/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jun 2024 04:01:32 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/geras/seven_types/</guid>
      <description>I see this as a terrific example of where reasoned and well formed criticism can stand on its own, in spite of the divergent trajectory which the author appears to take later on in his life through his reactionary offshoots.&#xA;As with any analytical field of inquiry which aspires to achieving insights, syntheses and increased understandings of the world, Marxism contains a broad array of unique and differeing perspectives, some of which fall far short of the high standard of rigor demanded of a scientific field.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Studies in European Realism by György Lukács</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/lukacs/studies_in_european_realism/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2023 02:07:16 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/lukacs/studies_in_european_realism/</guid>
      <description>The articles contained in this book were written some ten years ago. Author and reader may well ask why they should be republished just now. At first sight they might seem to lack all topicality. Subject and tone alike may appear remote to a considerable section of public opinion. I believe, however, that they have some topicality in that, without entering upon any detailed polemics, they represent a point of view in opposition to certain literary and philosophical trends still very much to the fore today.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Marx, Race and Neoliberalism by Adolph Reed Jr.</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/adolph-reed-jr/marx_race_neoliberalism/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Sep 2023 02:47:39 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/adolph-reed-jr/marx_race_neoliberalism/</guid>
      <description>A Marxist perspective can be most helpful for understanding race and racism insofar as it per- ceives capitalism dialectically, as a social total- ity that includes modes of production, relations of production, and the pragmatically evolving ensemble of institutions and ideologies that lubricate and propel its reproduction. From this perspective, Marxism’s most important contri- bution to making sense of race and racism in the United States may be demystification. A histori- cal materialist perspective should stress that “race”—which includes “racism,” as one is unthinkable without the other—is a historically specific ideology that emerged, took shape, and has evolved as a constitutive element within a definite set of social relations anchored to a par- ticular system of production.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
