<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>United-States on Class Letters</title><link>https://classletters.org/tags/united-states/</link><description>Recent content in United-States on Class Letters</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Jul 2023 07:18:50 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://classletters.org/tags/united-states/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Cuacasians Only: an excerpt from Robert Fogelson</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/suburbia/cuacasians_only/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Jul 2023 07:18:50 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/suburbia/cuacasians_only/</guid><description>&lt;p>A small but very important subsection from Robert Fogelson&amp;rsquo;s book &amp;ldquo;Bourgeois
Nightmares: Suburbia, 1870-1930&amp;rdquo;. I would say it speaks for itself.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Many subdividers also employed restrictions to exclude
‘‘undesirable’’ people as well as &amp;ldquo;undesirable&amp;rdquo; activities. By far the
most common of these provisions were racial covenants. Under
a typical covenant, an owner was forbidden to sell or lease the
property to a member of any of a number of allegedly undesirable
racial, ethnic, or religious groups. He or she was also forbidden
to allow a member of these groups, other than chauffeurs, gardeners, or domestic servants, to use or occupy the property. A few
subdividers had employed racial covenants in the mid-nineteenth
century. In Brookline, for example, one forbade &amp;ldquo;any negro or
native of Ireland&amp;rdquo; to occupy a dwelling, and in Baltimore another
barred the sale or lease of a house to &amp;ldquo;a negro or person of African
or Mongolian [that is, Asian] descent.&amp;rdquo; But such restrictions were
very much the exception before the 1890s. Indeed, not even the
most racist subdividers imposed racial covenants. A case in point
was Francis G. Newlands, the mining magnate and U.S. senator
who laid out Chevy Chase in the early 1890s. Newlands saw the
United States as &amp;ldquo;the home of the white race.&amp;rdquo; To him, &amp;ldquo;race tolerance&amp;rdquo; meant &amp;ldquo;race amalgamation,&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;race intolerance&amp;rdquo; meant
&amp;ldquo;race war.&amp;rdquo; Fusing the racism of the South with the racism of the
West, he called for repealing the Fifteenth Amendment, thereby
denying African-Americans, &amp;ldquo;an inferior race,&amp;rdquo; the right to vote,
and restricting immigration to &amp;ldquo;the white race,&amp;rdquo; thereby excluding Chinese, Japanese, and other Asians. Despite his outspoken racism, Newlands did not include racial covenants among the
minimum cost requirements and other restrictions he imposed
on the first subdivisions at Chevy Chase.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Socialism or Moralism by Bayard Rustin</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/socialism-or-moralism_rustin/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 03:30:51 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/socialism-or-moralism_rustin/</guid><description>&lt;p>Cross posted from &lt;a href="https://nonsite.org/socialism-or-moralism/">Nonsite.org&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Passages between brackets are drawn from the manuscript version of the essay and differ slightly from the published variant.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Published July 7, 1970&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We on the democratic left are living through a real crisis. And precisely
because I believe the Socialist Party has a very vital role to play in this
period, I would like to say something about the problems we confront.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One aspect is that many people on the [so-called democratic] left today
substitute psychology for politics. Now, I have no objection to a lifestyle, or
how you wear your hair, or whether you eat pig’s feet[, or whether you want to
dress so one cannot distinguish between male and female except upon very close
inspection]. But to substitute this “how I feel, what my thing is,” for
politics, is an extremely dangerous attitude which the Socialist movement must
fight. In fact, the Socialist movement is one of the few movements which has the
credentials for fighting it.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Race into Culture: A Critical Genealogy of Cultural Identity by Walter Benn Michaels</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/walter-benn-michaels/geneology-race-into-culture/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Mar 2023 10:59:16 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/walter-benn-michaels/geneology-race-into-culture/</guid><description>&lt;p>Due to the prolific number of footnotes that Michael&amp;rsquo;s article contains, the
essay will simply be linked to here. It is an important walk through the
trajectories that various essentialist concepts have taken in the course of modern
Northern American history. What surprised me most was this quasi-progess &amp;mdash; where
it appears that the concept of race has been disposed of, it&amp;rsquo;s kernel is
carried over into a different, yet sadly, familial form.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>