<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Development on Class Letters</title><link>https://classletters.org/tags/development/</link><description>Recent content in Development on Class Letters</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2025 21:52:32 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://classletters.org/tags/development/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Theory of the Innovative Organization by William Lazonick</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/lazonick/theory_of_innovative_organization/</link><pubDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2025 21:52:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/lazonick/theory_of_innovative_organization/</guid><description>&lt;p>An excerpt from William Lazonick&amp;rsquo;s terrific work &amp;ldquo;&lt;em>Business Organization and the
Myth of the Market Economy&lt;/em>&amp;rdquo;, a book that offers a critique of what a &amp;lsquo;market
economy&amp;rsquo; is purported to be, through an evaluation of the strategies and
economic histories of businesses within what can be called &amp;ldquo;actually existing
capitalism&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>Here, at the risk of a small amount of
repetition, I shall supplement that discussion by focusing on the nature
of fixed costs, the different sources of uncertainty the innovative organization faces, and the relation between organizational capability and technological change.
Through its investment activities, a business organization commits financial resources to specific processes to make particular products with
the expectation of reaping financial returns. Once they are committed,
the productive assets of the organization represent fixed costs that must
then be recouped by the production and sale of output. If, through the
sale of sufficient output, investments could generate expected financial
returns instantaneously, fixed costs would not represent an economic
problem to the organization. But then, we would probably not call the
“assets” underlying these costs “investments.” Indeed, we might not even
deem it appropriate to call these costs “fixed” or the entity that incurs
them a firm. The problem of fixed costs occurs because the production
and sale of the enterprise’s output occur neither instantaneously nor with
certainty. The basic economic problem that confronts the capitalist enterprise is to transform fixed costs into revenue-generating products to realize financial returns. An analysis of how and with what success the business organization manages this transformation is the key to understanding
technological change, value creation, and economic growth.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Capital Account Liberalization and the Developing Nations, an excerpt from José Antonio Ocampo</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/capital_account_liberalization/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2024 22:34:24 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/capital_account_liberalization/</guid><description>&lt;p>In looking to imagine and crystallise potential alternatives to the seemingly
unending vortex of underdevelopment and poverty in third and second world
nations, an understanding of the deficiencies and insufficiencies of the
current macroeconomic arrangement is an obvious starting point. The
post-Bretton Woods monetary consensus, which promised to guarantee mutual &amp;lsquo;real
growth&amp;rsquo; through endless liberalization of domestic markets and fluctuating exchange rates, has in whole been
failure for developing countries. Instead, of self-sufficiency and
self-confidence, there isn&amp;rsquo;t even what one one called &amp;lsquo;multi-lateral
beneficence&amp;rsquo;, but rather, a reliance and dependency on the most powerful players in the game, at the mercy of commodities swings and speculative exuberance
(rather than being &amp;rsquo;liberated&amp;rsquo; and domestically sound, buffered from &amp;lsquo;shocks&amp;rsquo;). One wonders what one
would do if they swapped shoes. What shall we do once we take control of these
responsibilities?&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>