<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Political Economy on Class Letters</title><link>https://classletters.org/tags/political-economy/</link><description>Recent content in Political Economy on Class Letters</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 May 2024 22:34:24 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://classletters.org/tags/political-economy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Capital Account Liberalization and the Developing Nations, an excerpt from José Antonio Ocampo</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/capital_account_liberalization/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2024 22:34:24 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/capital_account_liberalization/</guid><description>&lt;p>In looking to imagine and crystallise potential alternatives to the seemingly
unending vortex of underdevelopment and poverty in third and second world
nations, an understanding of the deficiencies and insufficiencies of the
current macroeconomic arrangement is an obvious starting point. The
post-Bretton Woods monetary consensus, which promised to guarantee mutual &amp;lsquo;real
growth&amp;rsquo; through endless liberalization of domestic markets and fluctuating exchange rates, has in whole been
failure for developing countries. Instead, of self-sufficiency and
self-confidence, there isn&amp;rsquo;t even what one one called &amp;lsquo;multi-lateral
beneficence&amp;rsquo;, but rather, a reliance and dependency on the most powerful players in the game, at the mercy of commodities swings and speculative exuberance
(rather than being &amp;rsquo;liberated&amp;rsquo; and domestically sound, buffered from &amp;lsquo;shocks&amp;rsquo;). One wonders what one
would do if they swapped shoes. What shall we do once we take control of these
responsibilities?&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Why no Roman Industrial Revolution? by Bret Devereaux</title><link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/why_no_roman_ind_rev/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Feb 2024 23:20:45 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/why_no_roman_ind_rev/</guid><description>&lt;p>Original at &lt;a href="https://acoup.blog/2022/08/26/collections-why-no-roman-industrial-revolution/">https://acoup.blog/2022/08/26/collections-why-no-roman-industrial-revolution/&lt;/a> . Linked to it via Paul Cockshott.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-question">The Question&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>That said this is a question that is not absurd a priori. As we’ll see, the
Roman Empire was never close to an industrial revolution – a great many of the
preconditions were missing – but the idea that it might have been on the cusp
of being something like a modern economy did once have its day in the
scholarship. As I’ve mentioned before, the dominant feature of the historical
debate among scholars about the shape of the Roman economy is between
‘modernists’ who argue the Roman economy is relatively more like a modern
economy (meaning both that it was relatively more prosperous than other ancient
economies but also that the Romans themselves maintained a more modern,
familiar outlook towards money, investment and production) and ‘primitivsts’
who argue that actually the Roman economy was quite primitive, less prosperous
and with the Romans themselves holding attitudes about the economy quite alien
to our own. But here we need to get into a bit more specificity because beneath
that quick description it is necessary to separate what we might call the ‘old
modernists’ and the ‘new modernists.’&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>