<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Neoliberalism on Class Letters</title>
    <link>https://classletters.org/tags/neoliberalism/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Neoliberalism on Class Letters</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 May 2025 06:20:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://classletters.org/tags/neoliberalism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Chile, an Investigation of Aid as Imperialism by Teresa Hayter</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/aid_as_imperialism_chile/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 May 2025 06:20:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/aid_as_imperialism_chile/</guid>
      <description>Teresa Hayter&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;Aid as Imperialism&amp;rsquo;, was one of the first somewhat critical texts written about the post world-war II monetary institutions, from a so called insider&amp;rsquo;s view. Having spent some time employed at the Overseas Development Institute, the World Bank financed Teresa&amp;rsquo;s research on the effectiveness of aid packages provided to Third World countries. Given it was intended as a publication on behalf of the ODI, one certainly encounters a report which offers an objective overview of the various policy approaches that these institutions taken.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capital Account Liberalization and the Developing Nations, an excerpt from José Antonio Ocampo</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/capital_account_liberalization/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2024 22:34:24 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/capital_account_liberalization/</guid>
      <description>In looking to imagine and crystallise potential alternatives to the seemingly unending vortex of underdevelopment and poverty in third and second world nations, an understanding of the deficiencies and insufficiencies of the current macroeconomic arrangement is an obvious starting point. The post-Bretton Woods monetary consensus, which promised to guarantee mutual &amp;lsquo;real growth&amp;rsquo; through endless liberalization of domestic markets and fluctuating exchange rates, has in whole been failure for developing countries. Instead, of self-sufficiency and self-confidence, there isn&amp;rsquo;t even what one one called &amp;lsquo;multi-lateral beneficence&amp;rsquo;, but rather, a reliance and dependency on the most powerful players in the game, at the mercy of commodities swings and speculative exuberance (rather than being &amp;rsquo;liberated&amp;rsquo; and domestically sound, buffered from &amp;lsquo;shocks&amp;rsquo;).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cancer Prevention and Screening by Jason Fung; The Cancer Code</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/public_health/cancer_code/cancer_code_pt2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 23:41:44 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/public_health/cancer_code/cancer_code_pt2/</guid>
      <description>This is part 2 of the post on Jason Fung&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;Cancer Code&amp;rsquo;. I found this a remarkable case point in the iatrogenic potential of public health interventions in which the effect on mortality is masked by a surrogate of survival; early detection. When tracked for long enough time, early detection does more harm than good, and thus, fails as a successful surrogate. You can find part one here.&#xA;I encourage everyone to read the entirety of Jason&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;The Cancer Code&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A False Dawn by Jason Fung; The Cancer Code</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/public_health/cancer_code/cancer_code/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Feb 2024 23:41:44 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/biology/public_health/cancer_code/cancer_code/</guid>
      <description>This post will be in two parts, both of which I find are illustrative of the difficulties of public health strategies. One makes particularly obvious the severe misanthropic consequences of profit seeking drives in the areas of health and medicine, and the second is a remarkable case point in the iatrogenic potential of public health interventions which may be completely benevolent in intention &amp;ndash; something that all states irrespective of political structure must address.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global Neoliberal Practice: Institutions and Regulation in Africa by Graham Harrison</title>
      <link>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/neoliberal-africa-global-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2023 22:51:40 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://classletters.org/posts/assorted/neoliberal-africa-global-practice/</guid>
      <description>This is a chapter out of Graham Harrison&amp;rsquo;s Book &amp;ldquo;Neoliberal Africa: The Impact of Global Social Engineering&amp;rdquo;. Although the book is more of an essay containing fragmentary thoughts, I found this chapter substantial in the sense that it clearly outlined the various institutional avenues in which projects such as neoliberalism cement their ideology.&#xA;This chapter considers the global emergence of neoliberalism. It looks at the ways in which neoliberal practice has emerged, expanded and established for itself ‘paradigmatic’ status.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
